<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A commentary vpon the seconde epistle of S Paul to the Thessalonia[n]s In the which besydes the summe of oure faythe, ther is syncerelye handled [and] set forth at large, not onely fyrst co[m]myng vp [and] rysyng with the full properyte [and] dominion, but also the fall and vtter confusion of the kyngdome of Antichriste: that is to say of Machomet [and] the byshop of Rome.</title>
            <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1538</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4054</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108939</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844591</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844591</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9420</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17182)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9420)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 29:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A commentary vpon the seconde epistle of S Paul to the Thessalonia[n]s In the which besydes the summe of oure faythe, ther is syncerelye handled [and] set forth at large, not onely fyrst co[m]myng vp [and] rysyng with the full properyte [and] dominion, but also the fall and vtter confusion of the kyngdome of Antichriste: that is to say of Machomet [and] the byshop of Rome.</title>
                  <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
                  <author>R. H., fl. 1538.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>66 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In S. Thomas hospytall by Iames Nicolson],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed in Southwarke :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1538.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by R.H., of the original by Heinrich Bullinger.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Thessalonians --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9420:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9420:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶A com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentary vpon the ſeconde Epiſtle of S Paul to the Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which beſydes the ſumme of oure faythe, ther is ſyncerelye handled &amp; ſet forth at large, not onely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng vp &amp; ryſyng with the full proſperyte &amp; dominion, but alſo the fall and vtter confuſion of the kyngdome of Antichriſte: that is to ſay of Macho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met &amp; the Byſhop of Rome.</p>
            <p>1538.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:9420:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Academiae Cantubrigienſis Liber</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="commentary_on_n2_Thessalonians">
            <div type="summary">
               <pb facs="tcp:9420:2"/>
               <head>The ſumme or ſubſtaunce of the ſeconde Epiſtle of S. Paule to the Theſſalonyans.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T ſemeth that thys latter epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell of S. Paule to the Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolonya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, was wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrayght way after the fyrſt, in the ſtede of a defenſe or bulworke to the ſame. For in that he handeleth certayne thynges at large, whiche in thys he touchyth more ſcarcely. And in the begynnynge he dothe yet ſtylle publyſhe and prayſe the fayth of the Theſſalonians becauſe that they had endured conſtantly in muche tentacyon and affliccion. For the whiche cauſe he promyſeth vnto them, refreſhyng &amp; eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lyfe, and to theyr aduerſaryes, fyre &amp; vtter confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: to thentent that he myght ſtrengthen theyr myndes. Further more becauſe that in hys fyrſte Epiſtle, he had made mencion of the commynge of the LORDE, and the reſurreccyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead, ſome dyd vnderſtonde that they were euen then at hand: therfore he ſheweth in thys, that the LORDE ſhall not come, before that the chyld of perdycion be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueled,
<pb facs="tcp:9420:3"/>
that is to ſaye Antichriſte, whoſe commynge and kyngdome, yee alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruccion, he doth connygly paynte forthe truely, euen that the world then to come beynge warned, myghte beware of that peſtilence. Laſt of all he dothe very often inculcate, that ſuche men oughte to be brought into an ordre, whiche with theyr ydelnes &amp; curyoſyte dyd trouble the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyke or comen wealthe. For he had made mencion of ſuche in the fourthe chapter of hys fyrſt Epiſtle. Thys Epiſtle truely is ſhorte, but yet very profytable &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. In the ſtyle it dyffereth nothynge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fyrſt, nother is it of any leſſe erudyci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then that. They ſaye that thys alſo was wrytten by Paule at A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenes, and ſente by men of the ſame towne: Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philactus thynketh that it was ſent by Titus and Oneſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:9420:3"/>
               <head>The fyrſte Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Aule and Siluanus and Timotheus, vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion of the Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians, vvhiche are in God oure father, and in the</hi> LORDE <hi>Ieſus Chriſte: Grace be vvith you and peace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God our father, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the</hi> LORDD <hi>Ieſus Chriſt. Vve are bound to thanke God alvvayes for you brethren, as it is mete, becauſe that your fayth grovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth excedyngly, and euery one of you ouerflovveth in loue tovvard another betvven your ſelues, ſo that vve our ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues reioyce of you in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacions of God, ouer your pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and fayth in all perſecucions and tribulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that ye ſuffre: vvhyche is a token of the rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudgement of God, that ye are counted vvorthye of the kyngdom of God, for the vvhyche ye alſo ſuffre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>HE prayſeth and reioyceth at the Theſſalonians, &amp; geueth thankes vnto God for theyr conſtancye and encreaſe of vertue. Of the which we may fyrſte learne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf we do any thynge
<pb facs="tcp:9420:4"/>
well we ſhuld geue the tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes vnto God, and not aſcrybe it vnto our vertue, but to attrybute vnto hym the pryncipall effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of all thynges, and in no wyſe waxe prowde for any thynge that we do well, nor yet thynke our ſelues ſtrayghte waye perfayt, yf we ſeme oure ſelues ſomwhat to haue profyted in vertue and goodnes: but rather let vs thynke to go forwarde euery daye, and ſtudy to paſſe oure owne ſelues in all kynde of vertues. Secondlye we maye lerne hereof that we ſhuld not enuey at other mens vertues, but rather reioyce with them, yee and to geue than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes for the goynge forward &amp; good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of oure brethren. Here are alſo recyted the chefe poyntes of oure relygio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fayth, charyte and ſufferynge farre other maner of thynges, then thoſe whiche the Byſhop of Rome, and a many of monkes haue re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herſed vnto vs. And in that he calleth the churches, not hys but Goddes, it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of humylite and fayth. For they are falſe deceauers whiche beyng but the ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of God and myniſters of the churches, do requyre to be called Lordes, and to vſurpe vnto them ſelues, any preemynence ouer other mens ſeruauntes. Thys place alſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9420:4"/>
doth teach, that ſayntes or holy men are appoynted to perſecucion, and to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſed wyth contynuall affliccions: and that thoſe trybulacions are a token or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtracion of the ryghteouſe iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, that is, that wycked men peryſhe iuſtlye, but the godly are counted worthy of the kyngdome of God, for the whiche they haue ſuffred muche aduerſytye. For after thys maner dothe he comforte and lyft vp the ſayntes, ſettynge the paynes &amp; rewardes before theyr eyes.<note place="margin">The afflicci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons of thys lyfe, are not worthye of the glorye which ſhall be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>wed v<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o. viii.</note> But yf ony man thorow the helpe of thys place, wyll contende, that ſaluacion is dewe vnto oure affliccyons, and not vnto the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and bloude of Chriſte onely, let hym marke thys alſo, that the very ſame man ſayde vnto to the Romayns, that we are iuſtifyed by the benefyte of faythe, &amp; not by the meryte of oure workes. It is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the fatherly liberalyte &amp; good wyll of God, that it is here ſayd, that eternall lyfe is geuen vs by ryghte, and we made worthye of the kyngdome of God thorow affliccyons: where as it is playne that all our apteneſſe is of God, and that we are made happy by the grace of God. But the goodnes of God, wold not diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte our
<pb facs="tcp:9420:5"/>
myndes, &amp; as it were thorow our inabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, prouoke vs to ſlackneſſe or weerines. And therfore the ſcrypture ſpeaketh as though we deſerued ſomwhat, and were worthy of the kyngdom of God, that we ſhuld do all thynges with a glad and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mynde.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is verely a ryghteous thynge vvith God, to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence trybulacion to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that trouble you, and to you vvhich are troubled, reſte vvith vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thys is a cauſe wherby is ſhewed, how that trybulacion of ſayntes is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the ryghteouſe iudgement of God. Whervpon S. Ambroſe ſayeth very good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly: becauſe that ſaynt Paul ſayeth, that a token of the iuſt iudgement of God, doth apeare, whether vpon the good or vpon the badde, therfore he ſaythe afterwarde: It is verely a ryghteous thyng with god, to geue vnto euery man accordyng vnto hys dedes. What is ſo ryghteous as that they whiche in thys worlde do ſuppreſſe good men, and banyſhe them out of theyr country thorowe perſecucions, ſhuld ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre ſuch lyke thynges in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to come, as they do them ſelues here: And that the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9420:5"/>
other ſhuld be in reſt with other ſayntes, whyche commynge out of many trybula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, ſhall receaue the euerlaſtyng kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom. For the Apoſtle doth ſet forthe reſte or refreſhyng, agaynſt the fyre of trybula<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, wherwith holy men withoute ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng are exerciſed in thys world. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhalbe gone from hence, all laboure and ſorowe ſhall ceaſſe, and quyetnes and toye ſhall followe. But to the vngodlye ſhall happen contrary wyſe. Wherevpon we reade in the Goſpell, that to the ryche glutton it was ſayde: Sonne remembre that thou in thy lyfe tyme receauedeſte thy pleaſure, &amp; contrarye wyſe Lazarus payne. Nowe therfore he is refreſhed, and thou arte torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted. It differeth nothyng frome thys, that we reade in the fourthe chapter of the boke of Sapie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And theſe thynges truly are to be layd vp in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faythfull, to the intente that in tyme of aduerſyte we myght per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuer in truth and ryghteouſnes,<note place="margin">A true ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge.</note> agaynſt the tentacions of the deuell. For the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peryte of wycked men whiche they haue in thys world, and on the the other ſyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trouble of holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; theyr mooſt infortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate eſtate, do greatly vexe our myndes,
<pb facs="tcp:9420:6"/>
for to caſte of the kyngdome of God, and embrace thys preſente worlde. Let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre therfore the ryghteous iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, and the chaunge of all thynges. Forſothe ther were in the tyme of the Prophetes, contemners of God and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thys worlde, which (after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our men) commendynge the felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of the wycked, and ſcornynge or conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the perylles that ſayntes are in, ſayde: Men ſerue God in vayne, for ther commeth no profyte by that we haue kept hys commaundementes. And we ſe that prowde men and ſubtyll perſons are hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and they that do wyckednes to ſpede well, and to be ſhorte, that ſuche are ſafe as do te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte God. And what other thynge is it, that men nowe adayes do obiecte agaynſte the true worſhypers of God: what good haue ye gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by your belefe? ſaye they. But what doth Malachie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere? The LORDE gaue hede and herde thys, and ther was a boke of reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce wrytten before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> LORDE, &amp; ye ſhall ſe in tyme to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, that ther is great differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghteous &amp; the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, betwene the ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of God &amp; the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpyſer of hym. Malachie the .iii. chapter.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9420:6"/>
Vvhan the LORDE <hi>Ieſus ſhall ſhevve hymſelfe from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vvith his mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty angelles, in flamynge fyre, rendryng vengeaunce vnto them that knovve not god, and to them that obey not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Goſpell of oure</hi> LORDE <hi>Ieſus Chriſte, vvhiche ſhalbe puniſhed vvith euerlaſtynge da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnacyon, from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the</hi> LORDE, <hi>and from the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye of hys povver, vvha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhall come to be glorifyed in hys ſayntes, and to be made maruelous in all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue (becauſe our teſtimony that vve had vnto you, vvas beleued) in that ſame daye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He doth here paynt and wyth expreſſe and very notable wordes, ſette forthe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes the commyng of the LORD Ieſus and the maner of the iudgemenete. The ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge ſhalbe vnto all ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes very acceptable and mooſt beſte wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and to the vngodly very ſowre and ſorowful. And euery word hath his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and pythe. Nowe (ſaythe he) the matter goeth all by wordes. But whan the ende of all thynges ſhall come, thoſe thynges ſhall apeare manyfeſtly, of which all ſayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes haue diſputed ſo long &amp; many yeares.
<pb facs="tcp:9420:7"/>
For the LORDE Ieſus hymſelfe to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e all power is geuen in heauen &amp; in earth, and to whome all iudgement belongeth, ſhall apeare in a corporall fourme and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes, for to iudge all fleſhe. And nowe doth he deſcrybe the behaueour of thys myghtye Iudge, that vnto all hys ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myes ſhalbe ſo terryble, and ſo deſyrous and longed for of hys frendes. He ſhall comme (I ſaye) frome heauen, not nowe (as once) crepynge vppon the earthe, nor yet lowe and deſpyſed as he appeared in hys fyrſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng: But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed about wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hooſt of angelles. For we reade in Daniell the .vii: A thouſande thouſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des myniſtred vnto hym, &amp; tenne thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand tymes tenne thouſande ſtode before hym. And therfore eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a myghty kyng, beynge apoynted with a choſen &amp; ſtronge hooſte of men, doth ſett vpon hys enemy, ſo ſhall the LORDE Ieſus vſe the myni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye of angels in ſubduynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; mayntenaunce of the godly. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth he call them the myghty angels of God, as he wold ſaye: they, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god doth exercyſe hys power or myghte. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come forth gently &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunte and for to heale y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnruly, but be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9420:7"/>
armed with horryble and flamynge fyre. The Apoſtle Peter beareth wytneſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that the LORDE ſhall iudge the world by fyre .ii. Petri .iiii. And the Prophete Dauid deſcrybynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maner of Chriſtes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng to iudgement, Pſal. xviii. ſayeth: Fyre ſhal go forth before him, he ſhall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de forth hys arowes &amp; ſkatter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhal caſt oute lyghtenynges &amp; deſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And Daniel: A fyry flowde brake forth (ſayeth he) &amp; we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſyghte. Furthermore Paul doth in playne wordes declare who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> LORD ſhal deſtroy at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge. He ſhall of his wrath re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which knew not god, or at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſt wold not know god, which followynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded not hys preceptes, &amp; obeyed not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpell of oure LORDE Ieſus Chriſte. Which thyng agreeth very well to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that is now in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. For the Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s obeyed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpell, &amp; ſuffered perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for it. It was ſwete therfore to heare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr obedience ſhuld be healthfull vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to theyr aduerſaries y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perſecuted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> damnable. For he repetyng agayn the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me thyng, whiche he had ſayd eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now in other wordes: which ſhalbe punyſhed (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) wyth euerlaſtynge damncion. For
<pb facs="tcp:9420:8"/>
eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo doth he rendre vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For he punyſheth theſe conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pners, when he appoynteth them vnto euerlaſtynge fyre. For ſo we reade in Daniell alſo the xii. chapter. Many that ſlepe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duſte of the earth ſhall waken: ſome to eternall lyfe, and ſome to ſhame and euerlaſtynge fyre. After the ſame maner alſo dothe the iudge geue ſentence, Math. xxv: Departe fro me ye curſed chyldren into euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge fyre, which is prepared for the deuel and hys angels: &amp; they ſhall go into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge payne. And S. Ambroſe ſayth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently wel: The wycked ſhall haue the paynes whiche are due vnto them, that is, they ſhall euermore fele eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall confuſyon, and yet ſhall neuer wholy fayle, that the payne it ſelfe myghte en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendre &amp; renew them after a certayn ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner wherby they may euer from tyme to tyme, be as it were conſumed. Therfore they deceaue and are deceaued, as many as do promyſe themſelues delyueraunce out of hell, and do fayne that after the day of iudgemente, wycked men alſo ſhall be forgeuen. The whych thynge men ſaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Orygen thought, I wote nere how truly: but it is ſure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> certayne of the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſtes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9420:8"/>
haue taught this openlye. But out of thys place it apeareth howe falſely and wyckedly. For the vngodly ſhall peryſhe by euerlaſtyng death. From the preſence of the LORDE, that is whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the LORDE commeth, &amp; from the glory of hys power: that is, when he ſhall come gloriouſly, for to ſhewe hys power &amp; ſtrength vnto good and euell. For wyth theſe wordes (ſayeth Theophylactus) he ſheweth howe eaſy it is for God to punyſhe, nether ſhall it be harde for hym to punyſhe: becauſe that re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bellious and obſtynate people ſhalbe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth the very ſyghte of hym. And the diuine preſence ſhall bryng vnto ſome bryghteneſſe wyth it, and to other punyſhement &amp; payne. For he ſhall come wyth glory and power, ſo that nother hys glorye ſhall wante power, nor yet his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence be without glorye. For it followeth that hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng ſhall not alonly be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto the wycked, but gladde alſo and gloryous to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly. He ſhall come (ſayeth he) to be glorifyed in hys ſayntes. As though he wolde ſaye: when he ſhall come for to rendre vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto the wycked, he ſhall ſhew him ſelfe gloryous vnto the ſayntes alſo, and make theyr vyle bodyes
<pb facs="tcp:9420:9"/>
lyke vnto hys gloryous bodye, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which cauſe he ſhalbe maruaylous in al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beleue, who then ſhall prayſe and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye hys ſo great goodnes and power? And thys ſhalbe ſo (ſayeth he) becauſe that ye beleued our wytneſſe, that is our preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge, whych I preached vnto you, tellyng you that that ſhuld come to paſſe, whych God ſhall do in that day. Ther are which thynke that theſe wordes: becauſe that ye beleued oure teſtymony, are put in by a <hi>Parentheſis,</hi> and that to declare who be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true beleuers, that is to ſaye, ſuch as geue credence to the Apoſtles wytneſſe. Saynt Ambroſe ſayeth that it may be expounded two wayes. For he ſhall come (ſayeth he) to punyſh the euell and glorifye the good. For he ſhall ſeme and ſhew hym ſelfe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous and maruelous, toward them that beleue, after the enſample and fayth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles, at what tyme they ſhalbe crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with glory, the Goſpell bearyng wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the day of the LORDE. And he ſhall appeare to the vnfaythfull a ſore and heuy Iudge, at ſuchtyme as they ſhall begynne to fele the bytterneſſe of euerlaſtynge payne. For the glorye of the mayſter is a reioyce and in maner of a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9420:9"/>
crowne vnto the diſciples, and hys truthe the extreme payne and myſery of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleuers: becauſe they beleued not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true preachers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vvherfore vve praye alvvayes for you, that oure God vvyll counte you vvorthy of thys callynge, and fulfyll e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery good purpoſe to goodnes, and the vvorke of fayth in povver, that the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of our</hi> LORD <hi>Ieſus Chriſt may be glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rifyed by you and ye by hym, thorovve the grace of our God and</hi> LORDE <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To harde thynges he alwayes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth prayer. For faythe it ſelfe and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence that we owe vnto God do teach vs, that thorowe prayer we owghte to go aboute to optayne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chefe gyftes of God. And we ſhuld praye wythoute ceaſſynge. For S. Paule ſayeth: We praye alwayes for you. And what we ſhulde praye or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre, it followeth: That oure God wyll counte you worthy of thys callyng. What callynge I pray you? The ſame no doubt, wherwyth he ſhall call y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed into hys kyngdome, ſayenge: Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me ye bleſſed chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of my father, poſſeſſe the kyngdome that is prepared for you, from the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge
<pb facs="tcp:9420:10"/>
of the worlde. Math. xxv. Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re now thys place wyth that: Ye ſuffre, that ye myghte be counted worthy of the kyngdome of God, and ye ſhall perceaue that the fre grace of God maketh vs wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the kyngdome of God. For yf oure merites make vs worthy, what nede wer ther to praye the LORD y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te vs worthy of hys callyng. That worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe therfore hangeth vpon the fre libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralite of God. After thys we muſt praye, that God wyl fulfyll all oure good purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes to goodnes: That is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> accordyng to hys goodneſſe, wherew<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he loueth vs, he wyll fortunatly perfourme that, which he hath bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in vs. For he that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth vnto the ende ſhalbe ſafe. Math. xxiiii. It is not vnlike to this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> followeth: That he wyll fulfyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke of fayth in power. That is: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll make oure fayth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect thorow conſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of mynd: the which thinge once put into our myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des by God ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth all aduerſityes. Laſt of all we muſt praye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the name of oure Lorde, not oure name may be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed through our hope, &amp; that he may glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifye vs in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge: that is, make vs ſafe in ſoule &amp; body. He addeth thorowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:9420:10"/>
grace of oure God &amp; Lorde Ieſus Chrſte: moniſhynge vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all theſe thynges do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god, &amp; not of our own merite. Thys is alſo to be marked, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in this place alſo, he doth in al thinges make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne equal to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father: wherevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnite of God in the trinite is ryghtely defended of vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <p>
                  <hi>I beſech you brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, and for our aſſemble in hym, that ye be not ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly moued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your mynd, and be not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, nother by ſprite, nother by vvord nor yet by epiſtle, vvhich ſhulde ſeme to come from vs, as though the day of Chriſte vvere at hande. Let noman deceaue you by ony meanes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnderſtode by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of hys fyrſt epiſtle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde vnto iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; the reſurrection of the dead was eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. Ther were alſo many deceauers, which affirmed pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ende of all thynges was than come. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ther lacke none now aday<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of the ſecte of the Anabaptiſtes, which come where as is great reſort of people &amp; ceaſſe not to crye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the daye of iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. But Paule in thys place doth
<pb facs="tcp:9420:11"/>
ſhewe what muſte go before the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge of the LORDE, &amp; wyth what foreſygnes and thynges, man ought to be warned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And he doth very properly beſeche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Theſſalonians by that ſame thynge in whiche they erred, that is to ſaye, by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge of the LORDE, of the which he hath hetherto ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in the fyrſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alſo. Furthermore he exhorteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the vnite &amp; concorde, whiche we the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres haue wyth the heade Ieſus Chriſte. For we ſeme to be plucked from thys ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bodye, as oft as we haue no ryght opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the heade or health of the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres. And he beſecheth them that they be not ſodenly moued from theyr mynde, that is from the true vnderſtondynge and godly mynde. Eraſmus: Be not ſodenly moued (ſayeth he) from your mynde, yf that hys commynge be deferred. But the playner expoſycion followeth: Be not of that mynde and iudgement, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſhuld thynke, the daye of the LORDE to be nowe at hande. Nother be ye troubled. And to be troubled is to be amaſed in the mynde, to be afeared and to be deſtitute of counſell and helpe. After that he reherſeth diuers maner of wayes, by whiche the congrega<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9420:11"/>
are troubled.<note place="margin">Thre ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al cauſes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> troublynge of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</note> The fyrſt is the ſprete that is a reuelacion, prophecie or tellynge of thynges to come, with the whiche cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne mooſt vngracious knaues haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued many, boſtynge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to haue the ſprete of God, where as they were led wyth euell luſtes. The Montanyſtes and the Valentynia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which before tyme wer endued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch a ſprete (as Ireneus and Euſebius haue wrytten) dyd greatlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the ſymple people, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Anabaptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes do nowe. The ſecond waye to trouble the churches is worde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is doctryne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng forth of a lyuyng voyce, the whiche yf it be decked with eloquente and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraunte wordes, it is mooſt peſtylente. The thyrde way is a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfayte Epiſtle or ſome wrytynge garnyſhed with a falſe inſcrypcion or tytle. (as S. Ambroſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied) Falſe deceauers are wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te (that they myghte the ſooner deceaue) for to fayne an Epiſtle vnder the name of ſome noble wryter, to the intente that the authory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may ſet forth that, which can not be receaued by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. And it can not be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, howe ſhamefully y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> certayne vnthryftye knaues throughe thys crafte haue mocked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche of God, whyche
<pb facs="tcp:9420:12"/>
haue thruſte in amonge vs many bokes, many epiſtles, &amp; workes, as though they had come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtles or apoſtolicall men, orels from wryters that were noble and excellente in authoryte, learnynge &amp; holynes, whiche for all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they neuer knew or coulde aproue, yf they were yet alyue. For ther are abrode certayne canones of the Apoſtles, certayn Epiſtles of apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke men, yet &amp; many lytle bokes alſo, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Auguſtine &amp; Ambroſe which theſe men neuer ſawe: What ſhal I ſay of certayne ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s garnyſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the tytle of Cypriane &amp; Auguſtine: The neglygence of the age y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is paſſed, &amp; the couetouſnes of wryters &amp; prynters, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ygnoraunce &amp; vnſhamfaſtnes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ſo greate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man can deteſte it to muche. They that haue redde the wryttynges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toures, and haue ſene ony of Eraſmus iudgementes vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes of Ierome &amp; Auſten, do vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de what I ſay. And yet ſhalt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> fynde me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which thorowe the helpe of this place, wyll thruſt into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche of God euery thyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they luſt: Obiectyng that all thynges neceſſary to true godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes are not wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryptures, becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mencion is made here of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſprete of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:9420:12"/>
worde, and of the Epiſtle, by the whiche a more perfayte doctryne myghte be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered to the worlde then to come. But theſe men do not ſe, that thys ſame pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce doth monyſhe vs, that men ſhulde not be drawen awaye frome theyr mynde, that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholſome faythe once receaued, through theyr tradicions: whiche beynge couered wyth the cloke of the ſprete, of the worde, or of a decretall epiſtle, theſe men do caſte vnto vs as Apoſtolike and mooſt holy doctryne. For after thys ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they do auaunce &amp; only ſet forthe vnto vs bothe theyr popyſh maſſes &amp; all other thynges which they can not proue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtymonye of ſcryptures affyrmynge that they were inſtitute by the tradycion of the Apoſtles, and afterwarde confyrmed by the Epiſtles of Apoſtolyke men, and by the reuelacion of the holy gooſte. Let vs beware therfore of theſe rauenynge woulues, whyche beynge clothed wyth ſhepes clothynge, do come for to ſpoile, for to trouble, &amp; to deuoure. Let vs kepe fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanyng of Chriſt, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holſome and Apoſtolycall poyntes of true &amp; vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyled relygion, &amp; then ſhall noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deceaue vs by ony meanes. That learned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tulyan,
<pb facs="tcp:9420:13"/>
hath ſpoken more of thys matter in hys boke that he made of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> banyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Heretykes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the</hi> LORDE <hi>commeth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte ther come a departyng fyrſt, and that that ſynfull man be opened, the loſt chyld, vvhich is an aduerſary, and is exalted aboue al that is called God or vvorſhypped: ſo that he ſhall ſyt in the temple of God auauncynge hymſelfe as God. Do ye not remembre that vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I vvas yet vvith you, I tolde you theſe thynges?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The LOR<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>DE ſhall not come, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepte that ther come a departynge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yrſte.</note>Ye thynke (ſayeth he) that the daye of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng of the LORDE is nowe at hande, but ye are deceaued brethren. For excepte ther come a departynge fyrſt, the LORDE ſhall not come. Excepte there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ther come a departynge fyrſte, &amp; that Antichriſte do raygne, Chriſte ſhall not come vnto iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partyng &amp; raygne of Antichriſte or rather tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, ſhall go before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And here he dothe deſcrybe Antichriſte &amp; hys kyngdome at large. We ſhall touche euery thynge wyth a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pendious brefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, comparynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche Daniel ſpake of thys matter, with theſe thynges. For it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9420:13"/>
ſemeth that the Apoſtle toke muche of hys out of hym. And fyrſte we wyll ſpeake of the departynge.<note place="margin">Departing.</note> Departynge is here ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken after ſuche a maner, as whan a man doth ſlyde backe or fayle from hys author or prynce. Saynt Ambroſe doth expounde it of the diuydynge of the kyngdome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romaynes, and of the departyng of other kyngdomes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it. Other haue inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted it of the departyng of fayth, of the whiche the Apoſtle ſpake, i. Timo. iiii. ſayenge: The ſprete ſpeaketh euydentlye, that in the latter dayes ſome ſhall depart from the fayth, geuyng hede vnto ſpretes of erroure and deuelyſhe doctrynes, &amp;c. But both co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to one effecte as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge the ſubſtaunce of the matter. For when that ſame laſt monarchye or kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome beganne to be diuided, through the departynge of certayne kyngdomes from it, then began the Chriſten relygion and fayth to be corrupted and peruerted alſo, by them, which gaue hede vnto ſpretes of erroure &amp; deuelyſhe doctrynes. And by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame laſte monarchie or kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ment the empyre of Rome. For Daniell in hys .vii. Chapter. After .iii. myghty kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, that is to ſaye of the Babylonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,
<pb facs="tcp:9420:14"/>
Perſes, and the Macedonyans, addeth to the fourthe, that is the Romaynes. I ſawe (ſayeth he) in a vyſion by nyght, and beholde the fourthe beaſte was grymme and horryble and maruaylous ſtronge, it had greate yron tethe, it deuoured and deſtroyed, and ſtamped the reſydue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hys fete, it was farre vnlyke to other beaſtes, that were before it: For it hadde tenne hornes. I marked the hornes, and beholde ther came vp amonge them an other lytle horne, before whome ther were thre of the fyrſte hornes plucked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye: Beholde thys horne had eyes ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the eyes of a man, and a mouthe ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge preſumptuouſe thynges. Hytherto haue we reherſed the wordes of Daniell. And after he had deſyred to knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng of this vyſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he herde thys anſwere: The fourth beaſte ſhalbe the fourth kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome vpon the earthe, it ſhalbe greater then all other kyngdomes, it ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure, treade downe, and deſtroye all the worlde. The ten hornes are tenne kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall aryſe out of the kyngdom, after whom ther ſhall ſtonde vp another, whyche ſhall be greater then the fyrſte, &amp; ſhall ſubdue thre kynges, and ſo forth. S.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9420:14"/>
Ierome declarynge this place of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,<note place="margin">The Empy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re of Rome.</note> doth expounde it of the empyre of Rome, ſayeng: He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared the kyngdome of the Romanes vnto no beaſt, &amp; named it not: to the intent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what cruelte more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other we dyd ſuppoſe in the beaſtes, we ſhuld vnderſtonde that of the Romaynes. And ſurely thys empyre hath ſubdued and wayſted all the worlde: not beynge alonly vnlyke vnto other kyngdomes, in the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge vp &amp; gouernaunce of the kyngdom, but alſo in cruelnes, ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, &amp; fearcenes. For what nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hath it not waſted with fyre &amp; ſweard, &amp; vtterly deſtroyed, brought them in to bondage, and as it were a full and wanton beaſte trode them vnder hys fete? For the which cauſe Mitridates the kyng of Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus (as Iuſtinus dyd note out of Trogus Pompeius) was wonte to ſay of the Romaynes: That they dyd trulye boſte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr fyrſte begynners or auncet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were brought vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> woulues mylke, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the people of Rome had wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues myndes, neuer full of bloude &amp; euer gredy &amp; gapynge after dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ryches. Alſo Plinius in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vii. boke of his natural hyſtory, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxv. chap. ſayth of Iulius Ceſar.<note place="margin">Iulius Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</note> He fought in playn felde fyftye tymes: he only
<pb facs="tcp:9420:15"/>
paſſed Marcus Marcellus a captayne of the Romaynes alſo whych yet had pyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched &amp; fyghten .xxxix. battayles. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes hys vyctoryes ouer cyties, trulye I wolde not ſpeake to hys prayſe, of eleue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> C.xcii.M. men that were ſlayne by hym in battayles. Alſo the greate iniury that mankynd ſuffred by hym: whyche thynge to be true he hymſelfe confeſſed, although he made no mencion of hys deſtruction in cyuile warres. The ſelfe ſame Plinius in the .xxvi. chapter wytneſſeth, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple of Minerua, was a table hanged vp, brefly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taynyng the actes of Gneus Pompeius the greate which he had done in the Eaſte partes,<note place="margin">Gneus Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> in theſe wordes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowynge: Gneus Pompeius the greate Emperoure &amp; guyder of the Romaynes hooſte, in the tyme of hys warres, which contynued .xxx. yeares, dyd beate down, put to flyghte, ſlewe, and toke to mercye twenty hundreth &amp; lxxxiii. thouſand men, he bowed and toke .viii. hundreth &amp; .xlvi. ſhyppes, he had yeldyd vnto hym a .M.CCCCC.xxxviii. townes and caſtels, and ſubdued all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrye from the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Meotis vnto the reede ſee. And the title or inſcrypcion of hys tryumphe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9420:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
had the thyrde daye of the kalendes of Oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tober (Marcus Meſſala &amp; Marcus Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo beynge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſules) was thys: When he had once rydde the ſee cooſtes of Pirates, and had reſtored the Romaynes vnto theyr dominion whiche they had on the ſee, he brought gloryous ſpoyles out of Aſia, Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus, Armenia, Paphlagonia, Capadocia, Cilicia, Syria, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Scythians, Iewes Albanes, out of Iberia, the Ile of Creta, and from the Baſternes: And beſydes theſe he led vnto hys triumphe theſe two kynges Mytridates &amp; Tigranes. We haue touched only the actes, vyctories, &amp; tryumphes of two Emperours: we haue ſpoken nothynge yet of Scipions, Faby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, Marius and Metellus, nother yet of Lelius Sylla, Lucullus, Marcellus, Craſſus, Paulus Aemilius, Flaminius, Sertorius, Cornelius Cinna and Fym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bria, and of many noble men of thys ſorte and degre: by whoſe ſtudy, feruencye, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bycion, couetouſnes and deſyre to beare rule: To conclude, by whoſe wylde cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; extreme tyrannye it came to paſſe that (accordynge to the prophecye of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell) all the world was deuoured, deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, and troden vnderfoote.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9420:16"/>Ye haue now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myſtery of that cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell beaſte, nowe ſhall we ſhewe what is ſygnifyed by the ten hornes, and what by the halfe horne that ſprange vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge them and plucked awaye other thre hornes. The nombre of ten ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth a multitude,<note place="margin">The diuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the Empyre of Rome and the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it.</note> and hornes kyngdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes: and it meaneth that the Empire of Rome ſhulde be diuided agayne in to many kyngdomes: that is, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thorow me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s departynge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, it ſhulde come to paſſe that manye kynges at once ſhulde rule in the Empyre of Rome. The whiche thynge beganne to be aboute the tyme of Conſtantine the greate, ſome gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the kyngdomes of the Eaſte, and ſome of the Weſte. And after that by pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſe of tyme manye nacions beganne to fall from it alſo, takynge other kynges and princes vnto them. Farthermore rude nacions brake in, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> agaynſt the Emperoure of Romes wyll: yee and ſubduynge the Prouinces and kyngdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of the Empyre of Rome they rayg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſtrongly. For thoſe thynges are well knowen, whiche wryters of ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes do tell of the Frenchemen, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes, Lombardes, and Perſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:9420:16"/>And ſo are thoſe thynges and ſtoryes, alſo whyche credyble auctoures bothe Grekes and Latins haue wrytten of the bloudye dominion of the Gothies, Hunnies, and Wandaies. And after thys maner dyd tenne hornes ſprynge oute of that beaſte, and the departynge was fulfylled of whyche the Apoſtle hath nowe ſpoken.<note place="margin">Of the ſpryngyngs vp of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts.</note> Nowe ſhall we ſpeake of the commynge vp of Antichriſte, that is to ſaye, of the reuelacion of that ſynfull man. Ther grewe vp a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne foolyſhe opynion that Antichriſte ſhulde be one onely man, the whyche ſhulde be borne in Babylon, and of the trybe of Dan, and that he ſhuld raygne certayne yeares to the greate hurte of the faythfull. But the foolyſhe men ſe not that Daniell dyd vnderſtonde all the Kynges, Emperoures or heade rulers of the Babylonians, Perſes, Macedonyans, and Romaynes vnder the names of one Lyon, Beer, Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parde and other beaſtes. Therfore it muſte nedes be, that he mente by that lytle horne, that is to ſaye by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, not ſome one onely man, but an whole kyngedome and an whole
<pb facs="tcp:9420:17"/>
bodye which ſhuld fyghte agaynſt Chriſte with theyr lawes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucions, maners &amp; ſtrength. Let vs therfore marke the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the Prophete: I marked the hornes (ſayeth he) and behold another lytle horne came vp among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, before whom thre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hornes were pluckyd awaye. And agayn: Another (ſayeth he) ſhall aryſe after them and ſhall be greater then the fyrſte, &amp; ſhall ſubdue thre kynges. Ye haue nowe the myſterye, and the expoſicion of the ſame. For the hornes do ſygnifye the diuidynge and confuſion of the kyngdomes. And in thys confuſion of thynges, by lytle &amp; lytle ſprynge the vp another kyngdome in the world whych doth ſubdue thre other kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
               <p>Let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare wyth thys, thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which the wrytters of hyſtoryes haue ſhewed.<note place="margin">Machomet of Arabia, ſome ſayde that he was of P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Nowe Machomet of Arabia in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeare of our LORDE .vi. hundreth and .xx that is to ſaye whyle ther was a maruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous confuſion of thynges both in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eaſt, and alſo in the Weſt, ſprang vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of Heraclius the Emperoure, whyche (as Volaterranus doth recyte out of a lybra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye) came of a lowe ſtocke, and beynge fatherleſſe one Abdemonaples a man of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9420:17"/>
the ſtocke of Iſmaell boughte for his cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and loued hym for hys fauoure and wytte: for the whiche cauſe, he made him a ruler ouer hys marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyſe and buſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one Sergius a monke, which for the ſecte of hereſie fled oute of the cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Conſtantynople into Arabia, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued hym with the hereſie of Neſtorius, &amp; loued Machomet greatly for hys wytte. In the meane ſeaſon hys mayſter dyed wythout chyldren, leauynge behynde him muche ryches, and his wyfe a wydowe of fyftye yeares of age: whome Machomet maryed, and after that ſhe was dead, he was made heyre, and greatly encreaſed wyth ryches: and beynge had in honoure wyth the foolyſhe people (by the counſell of Sergius) beganne to call hym ſelfe the greate Prophet of God. Therfore after that hys name was publyſhed, &amp; hys au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoryte greatly augmented amonge hys people, he made a law which he borowed partly of the Iewes, partly of the Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yee and alſo of the Heythen, and called it Alcoran. And thoſe that obeyed it, he gaue them to name Sarracenes or Agarens, and armed them agaynſte the Perſes: Agaynſte whom becauſe he had metelye
<pb facs="tcp:9420:18"/>
good fortune, he beganne to be taken for a Prophete or a man of God. And whan he had gotten hym great glorye, he dyed, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had lyued .xl. yeares. After hys death many prynces of that nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion when they had dyuyded the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tytude or hooſtes betwene them raygned ſome in one place, and ſome in another. And Homar the thyrde after Machomet, after that he had ſubdued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Perſes, toke Ieruſalem and all Syria about the yeare of our LORDE .CCCCCC. lxx Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine the fourth then reygnyng. After thys they that followed hym inuaded E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypte alſo, and ordeyned Calypha to be ruler ouer it. A man m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e reade more of the Sarracenes and of theyr kyngdome, here and there amonge the wrytters of hiſtories. And the nacion of the Turkes commynge of the Scythyans warred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sarracenes in Aſia, &amp; toke theyr profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and relygion of them from tyme to tyme as it were by hande from one to another: euen as they toke of them alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt porcyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr Empyre, &amp; kepe it to thys daye gettynge ſynce therto A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, Macedonia, Moeſia, Athens, Pelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poneſus, Epyrus, Thratia, Illiricus, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:9420:18"/>
many other contryes. Nowe by thys ye perceaue what that lytle horne dyd ſygni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fye, the whyche commynge vp among the tenne hornes dyd plucke vp other thre. For it is Machomet the whyche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng of a meane, yee of a mooſt lowe ſtocke, of a marchaunte is made a kynge, whoſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſoures haue holden thre of the mooſte myghtyeſt kyngdomes of the world, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, Siria, and Egypte: and yet I rehearſe not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other kyngdomes of whych I made mencion euen now. For by the nombre of thre, he vnderſtode many kyngdomes.</p>
               <p>But yet all thys whyle we haue not mad an ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myſtery of iniquite.<note place="margin">The byſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p of Rome.</note> For ther is another certayn thyng alſo, which pertayneth to the perfeccion of thys body of Antichriſt. Therfore whyle theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were in hand in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eaſt partyes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> By ſhop of Rome goeth aboute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dominyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Weſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Weſt partyes. Ye loked not that I ſhuld ſaye ſuche thynges of the By ſhope, but yet they are true. And who wolde euer haue thought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the miniſters of Godes word and of the churches ſhuld once haue come vnto ſuche madnes, as for to thynke &amp; cauncell howe they myght gette the gouernaunce of the cytye and
<pb facs="tcp:9420:19"/>
of the worlde? Specially in as muche as Chriſt had ſayd in ſo playne wordes: The kynges of the gentyles do rule, but ſo ſhall not ye: but I haue choſen you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſhulde go and brynge forth muche frute. And he that is greateſt amonge you ſhalbe a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte to you all. But theſe commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes of the LORDE beynge neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ther beganne certayne men to diſpute of the primacy of the Byſhope of Rome, at ſuche tyme, as that lytle horne was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge forth. And becauſe it was wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: Thou arte Peter, and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys rocke wyll I buylde my churche. And I wyll ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the the keys of the kyngdom of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And what ſo euer thou byndeſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, ſhalbe bounde in heauen: And agayne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that Achaſius the Biſhop of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople and Timotheus men of Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cia dyd deſyre of Simplicius the Byſhop of Rome, that he alſo wolde condempne Peter the byſhop of Alexandria the follo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer of Euthicetys, hereſye, as one whyche had rule ouer the chefe churche &amp; whoſe authorite was of greate value a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: certayne men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys, that the ſeate of Rome was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chefe of all churches, and that the Byſhope of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9420:19"/>
Rome was the head ruler ouer all byſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. Thou ſeyſt here alſo howe that lytle horne beganne to lyfte vp it ſelfe.<note place="margin">Ihon of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople.</note> And Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Conſtantynople puttynge more coles vnto thys fyre, helde a Councell amonge the Grecyans, in the whyche he declared hymſelfe to be the vniuerſall Byſhop or Patriarke. The whyche thynge Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius the Emperoure of the Romaynes dyd ſygnifye vnto Gregory the fyrſt By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhope of Rome of that name, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge hym for to ſubmytte hymſelfe and to be obediente vnto Ihon. But Gregory anſwered y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the power of byndyng &amp; low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng was geuen vnto Peter, &amp; not vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Byſhopes of Conſtantynople, and that therfore he ſhulde ceaſſe to prouoke the wrath of God vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym. Thys ſame Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory wrytynge vnto Anaſtaſius of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioche and to Eulogius Byſhop of Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria in the regiſter of the .vii. parte of hys .xxx. Epiſtle, ſayth: Youre worſhypfull holynes knoweth, that thys name vnyuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſall byſhope was offered by the holy Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Calcedonye vnto them of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolyke ſeate, whych (god ſo diſpoſynge) I do nowe ſerue. But none of my prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſoures dyd conſente for to vſe ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb facs="tcp:9420:20"/>
a name: becauſe ſurely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf one be called an vniuerſal Patryacke, it is a dero<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of other Patriarkes. But God forbyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ony Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld take that to hym ſelfe, wherby he ſhulde ſeme to dimynyſhe the honoure of hys bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren in ony parte, were it neuer ſo lytle Theſe are Gregorius wordes. But not al only the Byſhopes of Conſtantynople, but alſo of Rome the ſucceſſoures of Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gory forgettynge theſe thynges, dyd not ceaſe to ſtryue aboute the prymacy, vntyl that Bonyface the thyrde of that name, not longe from the tyme of Gregory, had optayned. But yet (as Platina ſayeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, not without greate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tencion) of Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas the Emperoure whyche ſlewe Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricius w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very cruelly: That S. Peters ſeate ſhuld be counted &amp; called the head of all other churches. Of the whych thynge Paule the Deacon maketh mencion alſo, in the .iiii. boke of the actes of the Lombardes the .xi. Chapter. Nowe whan thys was graunted vnto the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopes of Rome, ther was as it were a wyndowe opened vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole Empyre: And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they caſt theyr mynde for to rule ouer the cytye &amp; the whole world. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauynge an occaſyon, they gaue all theyr
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9420:20"/>
diligence to the ſame. And the wanders whyche were ſene at that tyme, dyd ſygni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fye a greate chaunge of thynges, for they were ſuche, as were neuer ſene before, of whych the hyſtoryes do teſtifye dylige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly.</p>
               <p>And ther were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very many occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whyche dyd lyfte vp the Byſhope of Rome very hye, then goynge aboute the ſame thynge, and ſpecially the ſedycious warres and the often breakyng in of rude nacions.<note place="margin">The brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge in of the Sarra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens</note> For the Saracenes the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of Machomet, after they had taken Africa, dyd ſpoyle Syria and Aſia and ſet vpon Europa. Therfore the Emperours beynge holden in the Eaſt partys becauſe of theſe preſente perylles, were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to ſet aſyde the gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Weſt. And by thys means it came to paſſe that the Frenche men and Lombardes encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed greatlye, in ſo muche that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure was at the laſte afrayed of the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of bothe thoſe nacions. For althoughe the Emperoure had ſet certayn Debytes for to gouerne Italy, yet was theyr pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to weake for to reſyſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The whiche thynge apeared well by thys one token, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Theodorus the Emperoures Leuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunte in Italy, had once foughte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with
<pb facs="tcp:9420:21"/>
the Lombardes at Scultenna a ryuer in Mutina:<note place="margin">The kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardye.</note> it was ſayde that he was ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully put to flyght and chaſed away, with the loſſe of .vii. thouſand ſouldiers of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: by reaſon of whiche vyctory, Rotha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris the kynge of Lombardye not a lytle proude, ioyned vnto hys kyngdom all Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guria. Therfore after thys maner the Emperours power beganne to decaye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Weſt, &amp; the Byſhopes of Romes power encreaſed, by ſo muche the more, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardes and Frenche men dyd raygne lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gely. For a lytle after he was exalted by theyr ſtrength, wyth whome he beganne to falle into amitye. But it came to thys paſſe by lytle and lytle, of the which thyng we ſhall nowe ſpeake. Yf the Byſhope of Rome had bene choſen by the clergye and people of the Romaynes, yet had the elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion ben counted as vayne, excepte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peroure or the Debyte of Italye had apro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it, vntyll that Conſtantyne the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peroure the ſonne of Conſtance, whyche beganne to raygne the yeare of oure LOR<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>DE. CCCCCC. lxx. beyng moued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holyneſſe of Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>net the ſecond Byſhop of Rome, ſente a decre that from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce forth all men ſhulde beleue, that man to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatlye
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9420:21"/>
the true vycare of Chriſt, which the clergye wyth the people and the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers of Rome ſhulde choyſe to be the pope, wythoute any tarynge for any authoryte ether of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prynce of Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynople, or the Debyte of Italye, as it was wonte for to be. And after that the Byſhope of Rome had gotten thys priuilege, he beganne to plucke hys necke frome the Emperours pocke, and the more boldly to parte: in ſo muche that wythin a lytle whyle after thys, when a mete occaſion was offered hym, that is to ſaye, a bytter contencion betwene the Byſhoppes of the Eaſt and of the Weſt, he beganne the boldelyer to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercyſe hys authoryte agaynſt the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure hymſelfe.</p>
               <p>For the hereſye of the Monothelytes ſprange vp vnder Heraclius the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure:<note place="margin">The hereſy of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothelites.</note> And that ſecte confeſſed onely one wyll in Chriſte. Martyn the fyrſt of that name gathered a ſynode of .C. and .l. By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopes and condemned it at Rome. The ſyxte ſynode holden at Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantynople co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the ſame. And that ſame infeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſemed then to be quenched. But Philip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>picus the Emperour beynge infecte with the ſame, after he had banyſhed Cyrus a
<pb facs="tcp:9420:22"/>
Byſhop of good iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t into Pontus, he made one Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a certayn mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke Byſhop ouer Conſtantynople, &amp; ſente hys naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye doctrynes into Rome, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they ſhuld be approued by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſent of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Here Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantyne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Byſhop of Rome the fyrſte of that name, gettynge a good occaſion to wythſtande the Emperoure, gathered a councell and condemned Phy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyppicus of hereſye and, Ihon the monke, yee and decreed alſo that the ymages of thoſe holy fathers, whiche had bene preſent at ſyxe Councelles approued of all men, ſhulde be paynted in S. Peters porche.<note place="margin">Contencion aboute the vſe of yma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges.</note> And therfore thorowe thys occaſyon thee beganne to be a diſputacion among them, of the vſe of ymages alſo. In the whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſye they of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eaſte parte thought more godly then they of the Weſte: But for becauſe that a ryghteouſe cauſe was ioyned wyth a wycked, it came to paſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it had the leſſe fauoure amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge many wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and learned men. And the Grekes fell not wythout affeccion into thys conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, whome it greued that the Romay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dyd abuſe ymages, as a token of vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye in the deſpyte of them of the Eaſte: for by thys meanes they turned all theyr
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9420:22"/>
cryenge agaynſt ymages. But I am not very ſure whether that the Emperoures Leo and Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyne dyd defende the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the Monothelytes: but thys is playne that they dyd abrogate ymages for auoydynge of Idolatrye, not wythout the example and authoryte of the ſcryptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded the Romaynes more then once for to do the ſame. But the By<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhopes of Rome by the meanes of thys oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſion dyd wythdrawe all the people of Italy from the obedience of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure, and thruſte in themſelues by theyr owne authoryte, callyng vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge kynges, by whoſe helpe the Byſhope of Rome was made Lord of Italy, &amp; the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peroures Debyte dryuen oute. For when the Emperoure Leo had geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente, that all whyche were vnder the Empyre of Rome, ſhulde take awaye the pyctures and ymages of ſayntes for auoy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge of ydolatrye, and that he that dyd other wyſe ſhulde haue hym for an open enemye:<note place="margin">The byſhop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes of Rome do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roures of Rome.</note> Gregory the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de admonyſhed all men that they wolde in no wyſe fall in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to ſuche erroure, nether for feare, nether yet for ony commaundemente of theyr prynce, &amp; ſteared vp all the people of Italy
<pb facs="tcp:9420:23"/>
wyth ſo great vehemency of oracion, that a lytle more wolde haue made them to ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue choſen them a new Emperoure. And at Rauenna trulye, after that a great ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycion was rayſed vp, Paule the Debyte of the Emperoure was ſlayne there with hys ſonne alſo. Gregory the thyrde follow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge hys exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple dyd depreue Leo as well of hys Empyre,<note place="margin">The byſhop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes of Rome do calle v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe of the kynges of Fraunce</note> as of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion wyth the faythfull. The ſame Gregorye called fyrſte of all vpon the kynges of Fraunce for helpe agaynſt hys enemyes. For why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Luythprandus kynge of Lombardye was moued wyth the deſyre to beare rule, dyd beſege the cytye of Rome, and had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken all the townes on euery ſyde: thys ſame Gregory ſente embaſſadoures into Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for to deſyre Charles Marcellus the father of Pipyne, that he wolde now the fyrſte tyme helpe Rome and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche beynge in trouble. And the Byſhoppes of Rome were wounte to aſke helpe of the Emperoure of Conſtantynople, yf any euell had bene commynge towarde them by any forayne enemy. The whych thyng Gregory wolde not nowe do, becauſe he had publyſhed Leo the Emperoure to be an heretyke, or chefely becauſe that Leo
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9420:23"/>
coulde ſcante defende hys regall cytye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sarracens, muche leſſe helpe other men. By thys meane therfore it came to paſſe (ſayeth Platina) that then fyrſt of al the defence of the church was tranſlated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Emperoures of Conſtantynople vnto other men. Then Charles toke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym thys defence, and delyuered Rome from the ſege: After that he had wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen Luythprandus the kynge and hys godfather from hys pourpoſe wyth a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge exhortacion. But the kynge of Fraunce through thys good turne, bound the Byſhops of Rome ſo much vnto him, That Zachary the fyrſt the ſucceſſour of Gregorye the thyrde, denyed not hys con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente vnto Pipyne the ſonne of Charles,<note place="margin">Pipyne by the meanes of the B. of Rome is made kynge of Fraunce.</note> in a matter mooſt vnhoneſte. For Pipy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne went about the kyngdome of Fraunce and deſyred greatlye for to put Clyperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus hys Lorde, whyche came of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyente and noble ſtocke of the kynges of Fraunce, and was the laſte kynge of the ſtocke of Merouea, out of hys kyngdom, and to make hym ſelfe kynge. Nowe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had troubled greatly both the nobylite and the laytie, yee and alſo the clergye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute thys matter, at the laſte he ſente
<pb facs="tcp:9420:24"/>
Burghardus the byſhope of Herbipolis wyth Folradus hys preſte vnto zacharye the Byſhop of Rome: for to aſke whether that he were more worthye to be kynge whyche was but the kynge onely in name and could do nothynge wyth hys counſell and helpe, or elles he whiche bare all the burthen of the kyngdome alone, &amp; yet in the meane ſeaſon lacked the dygnite of a kynge? Thys Byſhope of Rome remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brynge what had bene done for hym, gaue an expreſſe ſentence (I wryte the wordes of Fryſingenſ. a wrytter of hyſtoryes &amp; a Byſhop) that it was meter, that he which toke the charge of all thynges ſhuld be cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led kynge, then he whiche had but onely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of a kynge. For of an olde coſtume the kynges of Fraunce dyd leaue the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theyr kyngdom vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt auncienteſte of theyr ſtocke: for it was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hygheſte power nexſte the kynges. Nowe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe embabaſſadoures had broughte thys anſwere vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge, Pipyne bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge hymſelfe bolde of the verdyte of theſe great learned men and chefe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygyon, &amp; alſo of the ayde of certayne pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces &amp; noble men, dyd thruſte Chylpericus hys Lorde and kynge oute of hys regall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9420:24"/>
dygnite, and when he was oute of hys au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoryte dyd ſhutte him in to a monaſtery, and he hymſelfe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſente of hys me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> toke vpon hym all the kynges power. And when thys good kynge called vpon the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune fydelite that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had promyſed him, and that ther were many in the realme whyche greatly improued ſuche tyrannye and breakynge of theyr othes, Zachary the Byſhope of Rome aſſoyled Pipyne wyth all hys of theyr othe, whyche they had made vnto Chylpericus theyr kyng. And that thys matter was thus handeled I wyll brynge for the two wytneſſes: The fyrſte oute of the hyſtorye of Platina, and thys it is: Pipine beynge deſyrous to beare rule, ſente hys embaſſadoures vnto the Byſhoppe of Rome and deſyred hym that he wolde confyrme the kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Fraunce vnto hym by hys au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoryte. The Byſhop graunted vnto his requeſte after he had reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred what good turne he had receaued, and alſo the olde kyndnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had ben betwene the Byſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of Rome and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> familie. And ſo by hys authoryte the kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was iudged vnto Pipyne in the yeare of oure LORDE .vii. hundreth .liii. Thys
<pb facs="tcp:9420:25"/>
is Platinas ſayenge. Nowe followeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> latter teſtymonye of Gelaſius, wrytten vnto Anaſtaſius the Emperoure, whyche is conteyned in the .xv. queſtyon the .vi. Canon in theſe wordes: Another byſhop of Rome called zacharye, depoſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge of Fraunce from hys kyngdome, not ſo muche for hys iniquyties, as becauſe he was vnmete for ſo greate a dygnite,<note place="margin">The ſhepe troubleth the wa ter that the wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe ſhulde drynke in that is, an occaſion is lyghtely founde.</note> &amp; dyd ſette in hys place Pipyne the ſonne of Charles the Emperoure, and aſſoyled all the people of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theyr othe of ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Hetherto go y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes. And kynge Pipyne for to recompence the Byſhopes of Rome, helped Steuen the ſeconde, By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome beynge oppreſſed of Aiſtul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus kyng of Lombardye and fledde into Fraunce: &amp; after that Pipine had paſſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mounteynes twyſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an armye of men, he bayſted into Italye, and at the laſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled Aiſtulphus to reſtore agayne thoſe thynges whiche he had taken awaye: go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge aboute by thys meanes for to quyte the Byſhope of Rome for confyrmyng of hym in hys kyngedom.<note place="margin">Pipine ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vnto the Byſhop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, that whyche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged to the Emperour.</note> Then was the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce of the Debyte geuen vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Byſhop of Rome, and all that lyeth betwene Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus and Apenninus, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Placentyns
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9420:25"/>
vnto the pooles or ſtondynge waters of Venyce, and all that is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned wythin Iſaurus a floude of Apenninus and Adri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aticus, and what ſo euer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aiſtulphus had gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men of Hetruria, and of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byns: All theſe thynges (I ſaye) dyd Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine of hys lyberalyte geue vnto the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhope of Rome, the Emperoures Legates nothynge regarded. For as Pipine was remouynge into Italye agaynſt Lombar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, Gregorye the chefe Secretary of the Emperoure Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantyne the fourthe met hym, and in the name of the Emperoure warned the kynge, that yf he happened to haue the vyctorye of the Lombardes, that he ſhulde not geue vnto the Byſhope of Rome nor to the Romaynes, the Deby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſhyppe ouer Rauenna, whyche was op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed of the Lombardes and belonged vnto the Emperoure. But Pipine droue hym awaye from hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a metely ſharpe anſwere, becauſe he thoughte to do as he dyd a lytle whyle after, for the whyche cauſe he was the fyrſte of the kynges of Fraunce that was called, the mooſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten kynge.</p>
               <p>Hys ſonne that was called Charles the greate followed the enſample of hys<note place="margin">Charles the greate.</note>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9420:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:9420:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9420:27"/>
wyth a lowde voyce, he ordeyned thys Charles to be Emperoure, &amp; gaue him a kynges ornamenete: the people of Rome cryeng thryſe together: Longe lyfe &amp; vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye be vnto Charles Auguſtus crowned of God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greate &amp; peaceable Emperoure. Theſe thynges were done, the yeare of our LORDE .viii. hundreth and .iii. nor it is not lyke that theſe thinges were done without the conſente and counſell of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the Empreſſe of Conſtantinople, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially becauſe that the Cronicles of the Grekes do ſhewe that ther were meſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers dyrected from Charles and Leo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Irenes, to requyre her that ſhe wolde be maryed vnto hym: the whyche wolde ſoone haue grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vnto theyr requeſtes, yf that the prynces of Conſtantinople knowyng of the matter, had not banyſhed her ſtrayght way (and that before the face of Charles Embaſſadoures) vnto Leſbus, into an Abbey that ſhe had buylded. But Egynhartus in the lyfe of Charles, dothe laye all the faute of the tranſlacion of the Empyre, to the Byſhope of Rome. For Charles at the fyrſte (ſayeth he) dyd ſo greatly refuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the Emperoure and auguſtus, that he ſayde that he wolde
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9420:27"/>
not haue entred into the churche that daye, although that ther were greate ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempnyte, yf he myght haue knowen the Byſhopes mynde before. He addeth more: yet he ſuffered wyth greate pacience, the euell wyll that he had for takynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> name vpon hym (for the Emperours of Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynople were greatly dyſpleaſed wyth it) and he ouercame theyr grudynge wyth hys myghtineſſe, in the whiche he paſſed them farre. Moreouer theyr forayne war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res helde them backe, that they coulde not ſet vpon the Byſhope of Rome and kynge Charles. And therfore dyd Nycephorus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte Emperoure of Conſtantynople af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the diuidynge of the Empyre, make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyaunce wyth kynge Charles.</p>
               <p>Hetherto haue we ſhewed at large w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what begynnynges &amp; in what ordre,<note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion.</note> that lytle horne crepte vp, and gatte ſo greate power. Nether was ther then truely ony power ſo great in all the Weſte partye, as the Byſhoppes of Rome was. For at theyr ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce were ther myghtye kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes tranſlated. For fyrſte Chylperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus that was borne kynge of Fraunce beynge caſt of, he dyd craftely conſtitute Pipine hys gouernour in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges ſtede.
<pb facs="tcp:9420:28"/>
And after that he had taken awaye the power of the eleccion and ordenynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperoure from the heades of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynople &amp; the Romaynes, he gaue Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the kynge of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the name of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus. For the whiche cauſe he hymſelfe gette the rule of that cytie, whyche is the ladye of the worlde, for a rewarde of thys gaye done dede. Furthermore he wayſted that ſtronge nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and myghtie kyngdom of the Lombardes thorowe his requeſte &amp; counſell. Therfore he that once optayned Rome, he threwe downe and exalted Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peroures at hys owne pleaſure, and gaue Frenchemen a kynge, and vſed theyr ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce as they had bene hys ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. For wyth theyr armyes he tamed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bardes, that he myght afterwarde raygne ſafely ouer all Italy. He I ſaye that ruleth ouer ſo many and ſo greate kyngdomes, maye he not by good ryght we are a glyſterynge diademe wyth a tryple crown: No doubte the prouydence of God wolde, that thys Byſhope of Rome (wyth thys maner of apparell fyte for a kyng) ſhuld ſhewe forth vnto all the worlde what he was, that is to ſaye, that lytle horne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Danyell ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of, whyche came forth and put aſyde
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9420:28"/>
thre other hornes, and wyth wonderous ſubtylte ſubdued them vnder hym.</p>
               <p>And here vnto belongeth the gyfte of Lewes the ſonne of Charles,<note place="margin">The gyfte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges of Fraunce.</note> whom theſe men (for hys fauoure and beniuolence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the ſeate of Rome) called Pius, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye, good or godly: euen as before, they had geuen Pipine to name. The mooſt Chriſten kynge. Yf ony man deſyre to reade of that ſame gyfte, he ſhall fynde it dyligently wrytten of Raphaell Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranus, in the actes of Pipine &amp; Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, libro. Geog. tercio. The effecte of it is thys: I Lewes the Emperour do grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto the bleſſed ſaynte Peter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prynce of the Apoſtles, and thorow the vnto thy vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care my Lorde Paſcall the hye Byſhoppe and hys ſucceſſoures for euer. The cytye of Rome wyth hyr iuriſdyccion and all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lande aboute it, wyth the cytyes, hauens and places of Hetruria that lye nye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſee, yee and all that lyeth wythin the lande of the ſame, and the whole dukedome of Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenna alſo, euen as Charles oure father worthy to be had in mynde, and Pipine our graundſyre, dyd of late graunte vnto bleſſed ſaynte Peter. Furthermore we do alſo approue and graunte, the dukedome
<pb facs="tcp:9420:29"/>
of Spoletyne, the Ilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des alſo of the inner ſee, Corſica, Sardinia, Sicilia: the which all of them Pipine our grandſyre, of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remembraunce, and after hym Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the Emperoure oure father, dyd geue by wrytynge vnto bleſſed ſaynte Peter and his ſucceſſours &amp;c.<note place="margin">The gyft of Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tine.</note> In thys gyfte here is no mencion of Conſtantyne, the which verely is a fayned thyngt: for at the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth the Byſhoppes of Rome rayned at Rome and in Italye, euen agaynſte the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roures of Romes mynde by the helpe of the kynges of Fraunce. The Byſhoppes of Rome in the meane ſeaſon, do ofte caſt forthe oute of theyr decrees the Canon whyche in the .xcvi. dyſtinction is redde after thys maner: Conſtantyne the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peroure dyd graunte the crowne and all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> regall dygnyte wythin the cytie of Rome and Italye and the Weſte partyes, vnto the Apoſtolyke man. But howe ſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter commeth to paſſe, we ſe that the Byſhoppe of Rome doth rule ouer all the kyngdomes of the Weſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The name of Auguſtꝰ or Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to the Germanes.</note>For it belongeth hereunto alſo, that throughe the counſell and dylygence of Ihon the .xiii. Byſhope of Rome, the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyre of Rome or the name of Auguſtus,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9420:29"/>
was tranſlated agayne from the French men vnto the Germanes. That is to ſay, to the prynces of the Almanes, Saxones, Bauares and Swychers. But howe they kepte them vnder theyr yocke alſo, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoryes of many Emperoures of the Ger<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manes do ſhewe full well: and ſpecially y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Canon whiche in the .lxiii. dyſtynction is redde in theſe wordes:<note place="margin">Kyng Otto.</note> I kynge Otto do promyſe and ſweare to thy my Lorde Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pope, by the father, the ſonne and the holy gooſt, and by thys wodde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyuely croſſe, and by theſe relyques of ſayntes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf by the ſufferaunce of God I come to Rome, I ſhall exalte the holy churche of Rome, and the the ruler of the ſame, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to my power: &amp; thou ſhalt neuer loſe by my wyll or my counſell, or my con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſente, or myne exhortacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nother lyfe nor membres, nor yet the ſame honour which thou now haſte. And I wyll make no ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute nor none ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in Rome, of ony thynge that belongeth vnto the or to the Romaynes, wythoute thy counſell. And what ſoeuer of S. Peters lande commeth to my power, I wyll reſtore it the agayne. And to whome ſoeuer I ſhall commytte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouernaunce of Italye, I ſhall cauſe hym
<pb facs="tcp:9420:30"/>
to ſweare that he ſhal helpe the to defende S. Peters land wyth all hys power. Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely theſe greate and incredible thynges, yf any man ſhulde compare thys greate alteracion and chaunge of thynges, and it were but wyth Gregorye the greate, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte Byſhope of Rome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name. But theſe ſwete Byſhoppes not beynge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent wyth theſe greate thynges, neuer ceaſſed to laye wayte for the Empyre of Rome by theyr mooſt ſubtyl counſelles, vntyll that they had preſcrybed lawes of the true elec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of the Emperoures:<note place="margin">The byſhop of Rome maketh law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Emperou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</note> and had decreed that the confyrmacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the kynge of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes ſhuld depende vpon them. And for the ſame cauſe Platina in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe of Grego<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyfte, wrote after this maner: Grego<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry knowyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weakneſſe of the Empyre &amp; the chaunge of fortune, to the intent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the hygheſt power ſhulde remayne the lenger amonge the Germaynes, &amp; that he ſhulde beare rule ouer other, whych paſſed other in ſtrengthe and dygnite, made a decre (Otto not denyenge it) of the eleccion of the Emperoure, in the yeare of our LOR<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>DE. M. and .ii. whyche thynge we ſe kepte vnto oure tyme: that is to ſaye, that it is lawful for the Germanes onely to choyſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9420:30"/>
oute that prynce whyche is called Ceſar and the kynge of Romaynes: and he ſhuld then at the laſte be taken for the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure &amp; Auguſtus,<note place="margin">Reade Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſilius Pata<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ninus. dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. 2. cap. 25</note> yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Byſhope of Rome had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrmed hym. I could alſo bryngforth other innumerable thynges of thys ſame ſorte, But I thynk y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the reader doth vnder ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de playnely ynough by theſe of whome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophecy of Daniel &amp; of Paule is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te.</p>
               <p>But ſome man wyll ſay,<note place="margin">An obiecci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> thou makeſt two hornes: Machomet and the Byſhope of Rome: where as Daniel maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion but of one onelye. But excepte that the Byſhop of Rome, beynge bolde of the helpe of the Frenchemen, had broken the power of the Emperoure of the Eaſte, he wolde ſurely more ſtrongly haue putte to flyght and perſecuted the multytude of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sarracens. On the other ſyde yf that the Sarracens wyth theyr runnnyge in, had not kepte the Emperoure in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eaſte par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, the power nother of the Byſhope of Rome, nor of the Lombardes, nother yet of the Frenchmen, could not haue encrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed ſo greatly in the Weſte partyes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore eche of them gaue an occaſion vnto other bothe for to ouercome &amp; to raygne. in ſo muche that of the Empyre of Rome
<pb facs="tcp:9420:31"/>
lyttell dyd remayne but a bare name only For the Byſhope of Rome kepeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cytie of Rome, &amp; the greate Turke Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople. Now both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> impugne Chriſtes inſtitucions &amp; lawes a lyke: both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do perſecute Chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, defendynge theyr owne lawes, &amp; ſuche as holde wyth them. Wherfore I coulde not make two hornes of them that are ſo lyke. Yee &amp; the kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Perſes &amp; Medes is fygured vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ymage of one beere indyfferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, although they ſeme to be tweyne. And ſo in the .xi. chapter, the ſame Daniell pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecyenge of the ſelfe ſame Antichriſt, and begynnyng at the Empyre of Rome, ſayth not: An arme ſhall ſtond out of him, but armes ſhall ſtonde out of hym, &amp; ſhall defyle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentuary of ſtrength, &amp;c. But you haue nowe the begynnynge and goynge forwarde of Antichriſte: here followeth nowe a clearer expoſycio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hys diſpoſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and kyngdome, by hys dedes and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The dyſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſycion and Kyngdom of Antichriſte.</note>For holy S. Paule, doth ſet forth An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt in dyuers wayes as it were in his colours: that he myght paynte forth, and as it were ſet out before oure eyes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, his dyſpoſycion and kyngdome. And
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9420:31"/>
to begynne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>all, he geueth hym to name the ſynfull ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, as it were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundynge hymſelfe, the chylde of perdy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The whyche names after the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of the Ebrewe tunge, are as muche to ſaye, as yf one in our tunge ſhuld call ony man, mooſte vngracious patrone, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happye perſone: yee and as it were myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefe it ſelfe and perdicion it ſelfe: as you wolde ſaye, ſuche a man as were the cauſe of wyckednes, and perdycion both to him ſelfe, &amp; alſo vnto other. Yf ony man wold reade the hyſtorye of Machomet or of the Turkes (the brefenes of the whyche Raphaell Volaterranus hathe gathered, Geog. libro .vii.<note place="margin">Of Macho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</note>) and wold ponder it wyth a dyligente iudgemente, he wolde ſweare that thys Antichriſte were the ſyncke of all myſchefe, and the greateſte deſtruccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all mankynde For he had troden down the lawe of God and had publyſhed hys owne, that is to ſaye, a mooſt ſuperſtyci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous law, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyche hypocryſye is mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely ſet forth, but yet in the mean ſeaſon a way opened vnto all wyckednes. He hath alſo ſubuerted mooſte myghty cytyes and layde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> flat vpon the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de: he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt holycongregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of god,
<pb facs="tcp:9420:32"/>
Antioche, Alexandria, Ieruſalem and Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynople w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the congregacions of Grecia and Egypte: for I wyl rehearſe no mo. Truely wythin thys .lxxx. yeares he hath inuaded, beaten downe &amp; ſpoyled more kyngdomes, then euer any myghty prynce, or cruell tyraunte had done before hym. We haue herde ſuche examples of hys cruelnes, that we maye very well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtonde by thys chylde of perdicion and ſynfull man, the kyngdome of Machomet.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The lyfe of the mooſte holy fathers of Rome.</note>Nother is the ſeate of Rome ony thyng behynde hym in myſchefe or wyckednes. Ther is no myſchefe nor vngracious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, but that they whyche are called mooſt holy, haue defyled themſelues therwith. I wyll here vſe no ſtraunge wytnes, I do appeale vnto theyr owne Cronicles and lyues. In the meane ſeaſon I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunte, that certayne men of good fame haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me vnto thys ſeate, but thou ſhalt reade of very fewe, that haue dyed vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte. For who can beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the beſt man that were could ſyt ſo cleane in ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane &amp; abhomynable ſeate, that he ſhuld drawe no fyltynes vnto him? But it came to paſſe that ſome were worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyuerſyte of theyr dyſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſycions.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9420:32"/>
Surely for the mooſt parte of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were not behynde the mooſte wycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt man and vngraciouſte knaue that is, in ambycio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in euell and trayterous craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, in warres, in bryberye, in extorcion, in mooſt vnſaciable couetouſnes, in pryde mooſt arrogau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, in fylthye luſte and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſnes. We brought examples out of hyſtoryes here before in oure expoſyci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where we ſhewed by what ſubtilties they came into the dygnyte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Empyre. And Platyna although he greatly ſpared the Byſhoppes of Rome yet beynge ouer comme wyth the euylnes, wyckednes, &amp; vnſpeakeable myſcheuous dedes of ſome of them, lefte that in wryttynge to hys poſterite, whiche he ſawe to be ouertrue. Beno y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cardinall dyd rather but touche, then deſcrybe, the mooſt vngraciouſte ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe of ſome Byſhoppes of Rome. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe of Gregorye the .vii. Platina dyd counte hym among the beſte &amp; mooſt innocente, but Beno rekenned hym amonge the worſte &amp; vnhappyeſt: as one whiche after ſacrylege and mooſt wycked abhomynaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, dyd alſo vſe wytchcrafte, &amp; all kynde of vngraciouſnes. And Marſilius Pata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinus the mooſt learned and beſte wryter
<pb facs="tcp:9420:33"/>
of hys tyme in his worke, whiche he made at <hi>Bauarus</hi> for Lewes the fourth, of the power of the Pope and the Emperoure, and called it the defender of peace, dothe clearly ſhewe what the Byſhopes of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me be, and were many yeares: that is to ſaye, proude, hye mynded, couetous, doers of wrong, vnfaythfull, troublers of peace, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commune welthe, dyſpyſers of God and holy authoryte, enemyes of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and honeſtye. Let men reade the .xxii. xxiii. xxiiii. xxv. xxvi. Chapters, &amp;c. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond dictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or parte of hys boke. We haue ſene alſo Byſhopes of Rome in our tyme, that nothynge more vnſhamefaſte, more fylthy, more abhominable or wycked thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges can be ymagyned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue done. For thoſe thynges are well knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whych Volaterranus hath ſhewed of Paule the ſeconde in hys xxii. boke of Antropologia. of Syxtus the fourth, and Alexander the vi. very fewe men haue thought well. Alſo duke Valentyne made them both noble men. Iulius the ſeconde was the beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Pope of all vſerers, dronkardes, whorehunters, mooſt cruell and bloudye ſouldyers: In ſo muche that they wyſhed hym that he had chaunged rowmes wyth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9420:33"/>
Maximilian the Emperoure, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of bleſſed remembraunce. For they ſayde that he was a man that was geuen vnto relygion, commune peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyllyte (as in dede he was a godlye and meke Emperoue) and that the other was borne for warre and troublynge of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Alſo Paſquyllus of Rome yeſted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Clement the .vii. wyth verſes hangynge vpon hym on thys mater.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Pope Clemente is nowe gone by the helpe of Gods clemencye.<note place="margin">Paſquyllꝰ. is an yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge at Rome, wheron be faſtened let<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters of thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges loſte or of lyke mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters that a man wyll haue pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhed, ether pryuely or ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let all mankynde reioyce, the whole worlde thorowe oute.</l>
                  <l>He ſhamed all the worlde, beſydes hys owne cytye.</l>
                  <l>And was the great ruyne, of hys ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, wythout doubte.</l>
                  <l>Thys is he whyche wyth prynces, no promyſe wolde holde.</l>
                  <l>But euermore betraye them, not<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wythſtondynge ony othe.</l>
                  <l>In ouerchargynge Italy wyth try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, was neuer none ſo bolde.</l>
                  <l>Greate ryches he had, but departe from ony he was lothe.</l>
                  <l>Thys is he, whyche hys owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey wyth cruell warres dyd oppreſſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:9420:34"/>And fylled all the earthe, full of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten mens bloude.</l>
                  <l>He ſpoyled many cytyes, thruſtynge out both more and leſſe.</l>
                  <l>Oh cruell perſone, who euer redde that he dyd ony good?</l>
               </q>
               <p>Infinyte other thynges of thys ſorte I do ouerpaſſe, leſte I ſhuld make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly reader for to vomyte. And ſurely no man (althoughe he were verye eloquente) can ſufficientlye declare, what multitude of wyckedneſſe hath crepte from ſuche hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the churche, amonge all the people of Chriſte: ſo that I haue not offended in expoundynge thys prophecye of Paule, of the Byſhopes of Romes kyngdom. I wyll ſpeake nothynge nowe of the ypocryſye, ſynnes and wyckednes of Monkes, Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Preſtes and the ſpiritualte (as men call them) becauſe that experience itſelfe doth ſet forth all theſe thynges more cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye then ony ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſcrybe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For here is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge fulfylled of whyche S Paule dyd prophycy: They ſhall reſyſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, men of corrupte myndes, reprobate as touchynge the faythe, but they ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle no lenger: for theyr madnes ſhalbe euydent vnto all men .ii. Timo. iii.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:9420:34"/>Secondlye Paule calleth Antichriſte <hi>Aduerſarium,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye an aduerſarye: and he calleth hym an aduerſarye or Anti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chriſte, as though one ſhuld ſaye, ſet playn contrarye agaynſte Chriſte: as one whoſe wytte, maners, lyfe, doctryne, dedes, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and inſtitucions do fyghte agaynſte Chriſte.<note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon betwene Chriſte and Antichriſte.</note> Chriſt came to ſhewe peace to all the worlde, as of whoſe commynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes had ſhewed before, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mooſt cruell nacions ſhulde turne theyr ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des into coulters, &amp; theyr ſpeares into ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes. Nowe Machomet doth boaſte hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be ſente of God in the power of armoure. Chriſte taught that men are not defyled wyth thoſe thynges that go into the mouth. But Mahomet hath forbydde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys, wyne and other meates, whiche god ordeyned to be receaued wyth geuynge of thankes. He hath alſo geuen vnto his, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and admitteth <hi>Polygamiam:</hi> that is moo wyues at once then one: the whyche Chriſt hath abrogate, and taught out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde lawe, that one fleſhe onely &amp; not two or mo, ought to be in matrymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. To be ſhorte al the lyfe and doctryne, all the lawes, inſtitucions and dedes of Mahomet are agaynſte Chriſte. Nother
<pb facs="tcp:9420:35"/>
do the ſayenges, dedes, doctrynes and ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the Byſhope of Rome wyth all hys bodye, agree ony better wyth Chriſte. Chriſte hath geuen vs in the Prophetes and by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachyng of the Apoſtles an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and perfecte doctryne, which alone is ſufficient ynoughe to gette euerlaſtyng lyfe. But the Byſhope of Rome ſayeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnto that perfeccion we muſt haue trady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions of fathers, I wote not what, as thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges wythoute whyche no man can be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and as though thoſe holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whyche lacked them were damned. Chriſt taught that one onely God ought to be worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and called vpon, and that by the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and interceſſion of hys name. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Byſhope of Rome hathe thruſte in to the churches the prayenge and worſhyppyng of ſayntes more diligentlye, then the true relygyon of God. The Apoſtles oute of the tradycion and ſpirite of Chriſt, taught that ther was but one onely hye preſte, &amp; one euerlaſtynge ſacrifyce onely, that is Ieſus Chriſte. But the Byſhop of Rome ſubuertynge that order of Melchiſedech, hath conſecrated innumerable ſacrifyces for to ſacrifyſe daylye for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynnes of the quycke and the deade. The Apoſtelles
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9420:35"/>
taught that God onely doth remytte ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and that to hym onely men ought to confeſſe them. But the Byſhope of Rome hath ſet forth vnto the churches wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous lyes of the power of the keyes, of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricular confeſſion, of caſes reſerued, and of the market of pardones. The Apoſtles dyd commende vnto the churches y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God, they taught that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beleuers were iuſtifyed by fayth. But the Byſhop of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me hath boaſted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merites of ſayntes, yee and hath ſolde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to. What nede is ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of many wordes? trueth doth not ſo much repugne lyes, nor lyghte darknes, as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt is contrarye to Chriſte. Chriſt dyd abrogate ceremonyes, he ſette in theyr ſteade a fewe ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt he wolde haue vs to ſerue him in ſprete and truthe, and requyred fayth and charite of vs. But the Byſhope of Rome as one forgettyng theſe thynges, hathe ſtuffed the churche wyth ceremonyes, yee and wyth mooſte foolyſhe rytes &amp; ſuperſtycions. And thoſe thynges whyche Chriſte by hys example, wordes and dedes had banyſhed oute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche, he once receaued them agayne &amp; holdeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faſt by the tethe. Chriſt flyeth kyngdomes, waſheth hys diſciples fete,
<pb facs="tcp:9420:36"/>
taught humylite: The kynges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles beare rule (ſayeth he) but ſo ſhall not ye. But the Byſhoppe of Rome perſueth not after kyngdomes onely, but the chefe Empyre it ſelfe, getteth it by crafte, and beareth rule ouer kynges that are ſubiect vnto him, yee and profereth hys fete vnto kynges to be kyſſed, and ſuche kynges as kycke agaynſte hym, &amp; wyll not worſhyp- this beaſte, he ſtryketh them wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bolte of hys excommunicacion, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them out of theyr kyngdome, ſetteth other kynges in theyr rowme, &amp; aſſoyleth theyr ſubiettes of theyr othe of obedience. Chriſte ware a crowne of thorne, &amp; was clothed wyth a purple garmente. But the Byſhope of Rome, decked wyth a tryple crowne, as it were Darius of Perſia co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth forth glyſterynge in hys golde and precyous ſtones, compaſſed aboute wyth an hooſt of men: Chriſt payed toll. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Byſhope of Rome doth exempte his from it, condempnynge and perſecutynge the holy authorytye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> requyreth ony trybute of thys anoynted ſecte. Chriſte beareth a croſſe: The Byſhope of Rome is borne vpon the ſhulders of mooſt couetous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Chriſte was poore, he fedde the ſhepe,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9420:36"/>
wente mekely into the towne, and caſte oute of the temple both byers and ſellers: But thys ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> boaſteth hymſelfe to be the Lorde ouer all the Weſte partyes, he ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth and deuoureth the ſhepe, and cloſed in wyth an hooſt of men is caryed proudly in a tryumphe, he receaueth into the temple of God all byers and ſellers, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wyll not receaue them he excommuntca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth them heretykes: To be ſhorte he hath ſuffered all the temples of Chriſt to be made ſo prophane, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nowe they be lyke to a well trymmed market. For yf I ſhulde ſpeake nothynge at all of the choppynge and chaungyng and byeng of benefyces, of the pardoners, or rather the deuelles marchaundiſe, of the fayers of ſacramentes, maſſes and indulgences. Ther ſtande ready before the churche do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, tabernacles, tables, chayres and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telles: in them are ſet forth to ſelle fygu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of waxe, lytle ymages, fete and ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of yron and waxe, hennes ans cockes and innumerable muche of ſuche kynde of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacions: and in the churches themſelues, ſtande Idolles wyth ſtretched out ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and becauſe they be domme, they haue an, interpreter by, that lacketh no tunge. For
<pb facs="tcp:9420:37"/>
he ſtandynge by the aulter and by the Idoll, for to ſalute them that come, recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them, allureth them, and fedeth them wyth fayre wordes, expoundeth the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of the ſaynte, and telleth forth the fayned myracles of the Idoll: to be ſhorte he mylketh away the money from the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtycious and foolyſhe people. And that ther ſhulde be nothynge to lette hym that ſhulde offre, he hath al ſortes of money by hym, and therfore he choppeth and chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth &amp; ſcrappeth all into the ſayntes boxe. Ouer the whyche Idoll ſomme monke or preſte hath rule, whyche of thoſe offeryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges doth noryſhe hys ſhameles houſholde, whores, baudes, yeſters, ſcoffers, knaues and ydle houſwyues: And before all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the mooſt holy father hath hys parte of theſe gyftes: the whyche hathe confyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thys holy marchaundyſe, by graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of his large indulgences, for all that our LORDE hath commaunded: Frelye ye receaued, frely geue agayn. Peter alſo ſayeng and pronouncynge: Peryſhe thou and thy money, becauſe thou thynkeſte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the gyfte of God can be gotten wyth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. But why do I proſecute theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſo muche, ſeynge he is not lyuynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:9420:37"/>
can ſufficientlye declare the couetouſnes, deceates, &amp; vnſhamfaſtnes of hys mooſte vngracious ſtocke, wyth theyr workes mooſt contrarye to Chriſte and true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygion.</p>
               <p>Thyrdlye, ther followeth in Paule:<note place="margin">He is exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aboue a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God or worſhyped.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is exalted aboue all that is called God or worſhypped: whyche ſentence may be expounded two maner of wayes: ether y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is exalted aboue God hymſelfe, and ſet vp agaynſte all true relygyon and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppynge of God: ether that he is exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted agaynſte all godly thynges, that is to ſay all true worſhyppynge of God, takyng the perſone and name of God, for true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygion and godly thynges. But why do I ſtande vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe thynges ſo muche? ſeyng that the Apoſtle hymſelfe doth ioyne vnto thys immediatly, that whyche maye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde all the forſayde ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: ſo that he ſhall ſytte in the temple of God, auaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynge hymſelfe as God. After thys maner (I ſaye) is he exalted agaynſte God hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and all true relygion. The temple of God is here taken for the worlde, for the catholyke and vniuerſall churche and the faythfull harte of euery man. To ſytte, is for to raygne &amp; to beare rule. To auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:9420:38"/>
hym ſelfe as God, is to boaſte hym of the power of God, &amp; to promyſe and chalenge thoſe thynges as peculyar to himſelfe, whyche belonge onely to God. Lette vs heare nowe howe theſe thynges are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fylled, in Machomet and the Byſhoppe of Rome. Mahomet doth not alonly deſpyſe the mooſt holye trynite, but denyeth alſo Ieſus Chriſte hymſelfe to be very God. He affirmeth that he gaue a more perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lawe, then was geuen ether of Moſes or of Ieſus Chriſte: he gloryed alſo that ther was wrytten of hym in the lawe, and in the Goſpel, yee and that his name was wrytten from the begynnynge in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> throne of God in the vpper parte on the ryghte ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. And among vs yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Byſhop of Rome or hys Legate had come into ony town, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> greate dilygence y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fell down before him at his metyng &amp; receaued him, not as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but as God. All the relyques were brought forth, &amp; all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kneled down to hym, loked for hys bleſſynge, &amp; thought it healthful yf they myght haue kyſſed his fete. And yf that ony man had but once thought, that he had not had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> full power in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; in earth, he was ſtrayght waye taken for an heretyke. What ſhall we ſaye
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9420:38"/>
alſo, that all preſtes wyth wycked Freres dyd preache openly in expreſſe wordes in all the temples of Chriſten men, that the Byſhoppe of Rome was the vycare of Chriſte, the heade of the churche, and that he had full power in heauen and in earth, yee and in purgatorye to: and that he dyd geue full remyſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes, that he could not erre, that all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> interpretacion of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was ſubiecte to hym, that hys lawes ought to be kepte as the lawe of God that he was iudge ouer all men, &amp; that he was vnder no mans iudgemente, yee theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were not aſhamed for to put theſe horrible blaſphemyes into publike &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyche thyng I wyll now bryng forth certayn euyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te wytneſſes. <hi>diſtinc XXII. cap. Oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi> Vnto Peter (ſayth Pope Nycolas,) the keye bearer of eternall lyfe, dyd God commytte iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth. Item <hi>capit. Sacroſancta.</hi> Although all were Apoſtelles (ſayeth Ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cletus) yet dyd the LORDE graunte vnto Peter (yee &amp; they wold the ſame amonge them ſelues) that he ſhulde haue rule ouer all the Apoſtles, and ſhulde be called Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas, that is to ſaye, the heade and chefe of the Apoſtles: the whyche alſo dyd dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:9420:39"/>
the ſame maner to be kepte of theyr ſucceſſours and other Byſhoppes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thys Apoſtolicall ſeate is ordeyned of God and of none other, to be the heade &amp; henge: and as the dore is ruled by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> henge ſo by the ordinaunce of God, are all chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ruled by the authoryte of thys holy Apoſtolycall ſeate. Agayne Diſtinct .xix. Agatho the Pope doth wryte thus vnto all Byſhoppes: All the decres of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolyke ſeate are ſo to be receaued, as yf they were confyrmed by the godly mouth of S. Peter hymſelfe. Item capit. <hi>In me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriam.</hi> Although that holy ſeate do laye a yocke vpon vs, ſcarſlye able to be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yet let vs ſuffre it and obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly abyde it. And a lytle after ſayeth Pope Steuen: Trulye becauſe the holy church of Rome (ouer whyche God wolde vs to rule) is ſet forth for a glas and an example: what ſo euer it decreethe or ordeyneth, it is to be kepte of all men for euer, and wythoute ony gaynſayeng. Furthermore <hi>.ix. queſti. capit .iii.</hi> Gelaſius the Byſhop of Rome, ſayeth vnto all the Byſhoppes that were ordeyned thorow out Dardania, theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des: All the churche knoweth thorow out all the worlde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Popes ſeate whyche
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:9420:39"/>
is ſaynte Peters ryghte, hathe power to lowſe thoſe thynges whyche are bounde by ony ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes iudgementes what ſo euer they be, as one that hathe rule to geue ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence ouer euery churche. And agayn: All the churche knoweth thorowe oute all the worlde, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy churche of Rome hath power to iudge ouer all men, but it is not lawfull for ony man to iudge vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of it: for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may appeale vnto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oute of ony parte of the worlde, but from that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſuffred to appeale. Item <hi>diſtinct.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Abuſed Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>non.</note> 
                  <hi>XL. capit.</hi> Yf the Pope (ſaythe Boniface) be found neglyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aboute hys own health and hys brethrens, or els vnprofytable &amp; ſlowe in hys workes, or ſlacke to do good, whyche hurteth hymſelfe greatlye and all other men, and doth alſo leade wyth hym by heapes innumerable people to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed wyth hym euerlaſtyngly in hell: yet let no man in the worlde be ſo hardye as to rebuke hys fautes: for he beynge or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned to iudge all men, ought to be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of no man, excepte he be taken ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge from the fayth. Agayn <hi>.IX. Queſti. III. capit.</hi> ſaythe Innocencius the Pope: No man may iudge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chefe ſeate, whyche deſyreth to moderate iuſtice: nother maye
<pb facs="tcp:9420:40"/>
the iudge be iudged, ether of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure or of all the clergye, nother of kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, nor of the people. Vpon the whyche Canon the author of the gloſe ſayeth: that a counſell can not iudge the Pope. <hi>Vt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra de elect. Significaſti.</hi> Wherfore yf all the whole worlde ſhulde geue ſentence in ony matter agaynſt the Pope, it ſemeth that men oughte to ſtande to the ſentence of the Pope. &amp;c. Ye ſhall fynde the ſame thynge agayne in <hi>cap. quanto de tranſla. Epiſcopi titulo. VII.</hi> in playne wordes: It is ſayde that the Pope (ſayeth he) hath an heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lye iudgemente, and therfore chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the nature of thynges in applyenge the ſubſtaunce of ony thynge to another. And of nothynge he can make ſome what, and make the ſentence whych was nothynge worthe, ſomewhat worthe. For in thoſe thynges whyche he lyſte,<note place="margin">O blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye.</note> 
                  <hi>Ei eſt pro ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne uoluntas:</hi> hys wyll ſtandeth for a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or a cauſe: nother is ther ony ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that may ſaye vnto hym. Why doeſte thou ſo? For he maye dyſpenſe wyth the lawe, and of vnryghtuoſneſſe make ryghteuoſneſſe: in correctynge and chaungynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes,<note place="margin">The Byſhop of Rome no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther god nor man.</note> for he hath obteyned full power, &amp;c. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto belongeth it that theſe ioly wrytters
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9420:40"/>
of commentes do ſo ofte inculcate, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope is nother a man nor a God, but the vycare of God, and a certayne thynge mengled and made of God &amp; of man. Yf ony man requyre the places, he ſhal fynde theſe damnable blaſphemyes, in <hi>VI decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talium lib. I. de elect. &amp; elect. poteſtate. titulo ſexto in cap. XVII.</hi> Item <hi>in cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinarum proemio.</hi> And what nede many wordes? Thys draggon vſurped vnto him ſelfe the full power of God in earthe, he tranſlated kyngdomes, and for hys owne profyte made and vnmade all lawes and rytes, and turned all the olde and true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> topſyturnye, &amp; hate daſhed &amp; defyled it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys fylthyneſſe: the whyche thynge no man can denye. He ſytteth therfore in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of god, auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cynge hymſelfe to be god.</p>
               <p>Now wyll we adde vnto theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,<note place="margin">The prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye of Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſte.</note> that whyche the godly prophete Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niell hath ſpoken of the ſame thyng in the vii. chapter: Beholde ther were eyes (ſayth he) lyke the eyes of a man in hys horne, &amp; a mouthe ſpeakynge preſumptuous thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And a lytle after that: He ſhall ſpeake wordes on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partye of the mooſt hygheſt, and ſhall deſtroye the ſayntes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt hygheſte, and thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maye chaunge
<pb facs="tcp:9420:41"/>
tymes and lawes. All theſe thynges are very playne, by that that goeth afore. For eyes do ſygnifye prudence. He mente ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, that thys kynde of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld be mooſt ſubtyll, becauſe that it ſhuld rule &amp; brynge all thynges to paſſe by fraude, gyle, ſuttel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, and craft And ſurely who ſo euer doth marke well howe that theſe Byſhoppes of Rome, out of ſo lowe a degre haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vp on hyghe, and optayned the dygni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of ſo greate an Empyre, he wyll ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue bene mooſt craftye and ſuttyll men. Nother coulde ony mans mouth ſpeake more preſumptuous thynges, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is playne here before, that Machomet &amp; the Byſhope of Rome haue done. Yee and though they haue arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly attrybuted ſo great thynges vnto themſelues, yet wyll they nedes ſpeake and be on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyde of the mooſt hygheſt: inſomuche that yf ony ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet nowe a dayes ſhuld call them the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaryes or enemyes of God, he ſhulde ſcarſely eſcape theyr handes alyue. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes thys, the one of them wyll be taken for the Prophete of the mooſt hyeſt, and the other for the vycar of God vpon the earthe: as men whyche had receaued this power delyuered them of God hymſelfe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9420:41"/>
and do nowe vſurpe it by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of God. But ther haue not lacked whyche haue ſmelled out thys deceate and wyckednes, and haue reſiſted it wyth all theyr power. But the mooſt holy father, and the vycto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Emperoure of the Turkes haue de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroyed them. For howe muche Chriſten bloude bothe of them haue ſhedde, it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the hyſtorye before mencyonede and how much they ſhedde yet ſtylle, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckye experience dothe teache vs well ynough. Nowe although in very dede that no man hath the power for to make &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make the good lawes of God at hys plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, yet hath Antichriſt vſurped y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power vpon hym. Wherevpon ſayth Daniell: he ſhall thynke that he maye chaunge the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and lawes: but he ſayeth not, he ſhall haue power to chaunge them. Now Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chomet and the Byſhoppe of Rome haue vſurped y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power vnto them mooſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, which thynge we haue proued a lytle before by ſufficiente teſtymonyes. In the eleuenth chapter the ſame Daniel ſayeth: The kynge ſhall do what hym lyſte: he ſhall exalte &amp; magnifye hymſelfe agaynſt all that is God, he ſhall ſpeake maruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous thynges agaynſt the God of goddes,
<pb facs="tcp:9420:42"/>
and he ſhall proſpere, vntyll the wrathe be fulfylled, for hys fall is appoynted and ſo forthe. For the Prophete hath ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more vpon thys matter in that place, whyche may be vnderſtonde of euery wyttye ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wythout ony laboure or expoſycion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy of Pauie wreſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the preachers of the Goſpel.</note>And here we maye not paſſe ouer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Papyſtes do expounde thys place of Paule vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. For nowe ſaye they, is this departynge fulfylled, when the Luthery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and the Zwynglyans do departe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy ſeate of Rome, and wyth theyr li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertye do open a gate vnto all ſynne and myſchefe, and are agaynſte the Prelates of the churche: beſydes thys, they are lyfte vp agaynſte the vycar of God hymſelfe, defylynge the authoryte of the churche, whyche neuer erred, and ſyttynge in the temple of God, do boaſte themſelues to preache the worde of God, &amp; therfore they thynke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues worthye to be worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped as God. But they do vs wronge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we neuer departed a ſtrawe bredth from the truthe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> canonicall ſcripture. For althoughe we knowe not the churche of Rome, as it is nowe ordered, yet we do knowlede the holy catholyke churche and the onely heade therof Ieſus Chriſt. The
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9420:42"/>
whyche in as muche as he promyſed that he wolde abyde wyth vs vnto the ende of the worlde, Math. xxviii. we nede not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that he hath put a vycare or Debyte in hys ſteade. For a vycare ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in the ſteade of hym that is abſente. But Chriſt is euermore preſente wyth hys churche: hym onely do we preache, comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and inculcate vnto our churches. We do moue men contynually to beleue in hym, &amp; we do teache mooſt dylygentlye, charyte, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cye and pure lyuynge. Nother do we teache ony other lybertye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of whyche the Apoſtle ſpake: Ye are called into lyber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye, but ſe that ye geue not your lybertye an occaſion to the fleſhe, but thorow cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte ſerue you one another, Galat. v. And we are agaynſte none of the chefe of the churche. For the Prelates of the churche, are the mynyſters of the worde &amp; teachers of the truthe of the Goſpell: and who deſpyſeth ſuche? who is agaynſt ſuch? But yf ony vnder the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the church and of mynyſtracion do ſeke theyr owne, beare rule, oppreſſe the truthe, &amp; ſettynge godlye thynges aſyde, do teache mennes tradycio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, forſothe they are of good ryght deſpyſed throughe theyr owne defaute.
<pb facs="tcp:9420:43"/>
For Peter ſayeth: We muſte obey God more then man. And our LORDE in the Goſpell: Se y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man deceaue you. For many ſhall come in my name, ſayenge I am Chriſt, &amp; ſhal deceaue many. Farther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more we dyd neuer defyle the authoryte of the catholyke church. For we do hyghly eſteme Chriſte hymſelfe and the canony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call truth. Nowe the ſtrength and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the churche is Chriſte &amp; the truthe. Howe ſhulde not we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudge honorably of the church? We haue neuer ſytten in the temple of God, but haue mynyſtred alwayes: and for thys cauſe haue we chef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cryed agaynſte you, becauſe that ye wyl beare rule or ſytte, &amp; not mynyſtre as we do. Moreouer we do frely confeſſe that we leauynge mens tradycions do purely and ſymply (that is to ſaye as muche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God and oure fraylnes wyll ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre) preache the canonicall ſcrypture, and for the eſtablyſhynge not of our authoryte but of it, do often ſaye wyth ſaynte Paul: He that refuſeth theſe thynges, refuſeth not man, but God, whyche hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys holy ſprete vnto the Prophetes and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhulde teache theſe thynges vnto vs .i. Theſſalo. iiii. Yet we do geue
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:9420:43"/>
all honoure to God onely in all thynges, and vnto our ſelues nothynge but confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Our churches, whyche are Chriſtes, wyll teſtifye thys.</p>
               <p>Laſte of all I wyll put to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paraphraſe of ſaynte Ierome,<note place="margin">The para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe of S. Ierome vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le.</note> wyth the whyche he dyd expounde theſe wordes of ſaynt Paule in the <hi>.XI. queſtion.</hi> vnto Algaſia, after thys maner: Excepte (ſaythe he) ther come a departynge fyrſte, and that all nacions whych are ſubiecte to the Empyre of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me do departe from it, and that he be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueled, that is to ſaye opened, whom all the wordes of the prophetes do ſhewe forthe: <hi>The man of ſynne,</hi> in whome is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of all ſynnes, <hi>And chyld of perdy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,</hi> that is, of the deuell (for he is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruccion of all men) whyche is agaynſte Chriſte, and is therfore called Antichriſt, and is exalted aboue all that is called god ſo that he treadeth downe wyth hys foote the goddes of all nacions, or els all comly and true relygion, and in the temple of God (whyche is Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſome thynke) or els in the churche (as we rather ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe) ſheweth hymſelfe as thoughe he were Chriſte and the ſonne of God. Excepte (ſayeth he) that the Empyre of Rome be
<pb facs="tcp:9420:44"/>
fyrſt made deſolate, and that Antichriſte go before, Chriſte ſhall not come, whyche ſhall therfore ſo come, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maye deſtroye Antichriſte. Ye remembre ſayeth he, that theſe thynges whyche I nowe wrytte by myne Epyſtle, when I was wyth you I ſhewed you in expreſſe wordes, and tolde you that Chriſte ſhulde not come, excepte that Antichriſte wente before. Hetherto haue I rehearſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of S. Ierome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And novve you knovve vvhat vvythholdeth: euen that he myghte be vttered at hys tyme. For the myſterye or iniquite dothe already vvorke. Let hym vvhyche novve holdeth, holde ſtyll, vntyll it be taken avvaye, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall that vvycked be vttered, vvhome the</hi> LORDE <hi>ſhall conſume vvyth the ſprete of hys mouth, and ſhall deſtroye vvyth the clearneſſe of hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">He wryteth mor playnly of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of Antichriſte when he ſhuld come.</note>Some man myght ſaye, why ſhuld we not beleue, that the aduerſary of Chriſt, doth now raygne, and is alreadye come, when we do ſe the name of Chriſte, &amp; hys doctryne by all meanes to be ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte, of all the myghtyeſt men of thys worlde? The Apoſtle doth anſwere: You knowe what letteth: euen that I tolde you
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9420:44"/>
that he ſhulde be vttered, when hys tyme is come. Forſothe a man can not denye, but that euen nowe the power of iniquy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te doth worke by hym, but nowe he ſetteth forth hys ſtrength more couertlye, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhall do when his tyme is come. For vnto the bodye of Antichriſte belonge blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, cruell perſecucions, hereſyes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch lyke iniquities. But theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges beganne to budde and ſprynge vp by and by, euen in the tyme of the Apoſtles. Wherevpon Ihon the Apoſtle ſayeth: My lytle chyldren, it is nowe the laſte tyme, &amp; as you haue herde, that Antichriſte ſhall come, euen nowe ther begynne to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Antichriſtes alreadye .i. Iho. ii. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dothe Paule more clearlye ſygnyfye vnto vs, that ſame tyme in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyche An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſte, that is to ſaye, the perfeccion of all iniquite ſhuld be vttered, ſayeng: Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhalbe taken awaye, whyche nowe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>holdeth or letteth hym for to raygne, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wycked be opened. That is to ſaye, whan that the Empyre of Rome ſhall be taken out of the waye, or at the leeſt way troubled, then ſhall Antichriſte raygne, &amp; after that ſhall Chriſte come bothe for to deſtroye thys enemye of all ſayntes, and
<pb facs="tcp:9420:45"/>
alſo for to iudge all fleſh. For he doth now expownde that more playnely, whyche he ſpake of before. The wordes correſponde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the greke texte, do make thoſe thynges more playne for thus they ſygnyfye: hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge that now, tyll it be out of the waye: whyche is as muche to ſaye, as that that thynge whyche nowe onlye letteth, ſhall be taken out of the waye. And then ſhall y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wycked appeare. Or els (to ſpeake it more playne) that thynge wyhche nowe onely letteth ſhall be a lette ſo longe, vntyll it be taken awaye:<note place="margin">Saynte Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome.</note> and when it is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaye, then ſhall Antichriſt come forth. And S. Ierom alſo followeth the ſame ſence, wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge vnto Algaſia theſe wordes in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: What is the cauſe that Antichriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not now, ye knowe full well. Nother wolde he playnely ſaye, that the Empyre of Rome ſhulde be deſtroyed, becauſe that they whyche gouerne it do thynke it euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge. For the whyche cauſe after the Apocalypſe of S. Ihon, ther was wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreheade of the whore that was clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in purple, a name of blaſphemy, that is to ſaye, Rome eternall. For yf he had ſayde playnely and boldly, Antichriſt ſhall not come, excepte the Empyre of Rome
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:9420:45"/>
be fyrſt done away, it ſemeth that he ſhuld haue geuen a iuſte cauſe of perſecucion, agaynſt the churche in the Eaſte partyes. And a lytle after he ſayeth: The Empyre of Rome whyche nowe hath all nacions vnder it, ſhal ceaſſe and be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the waye, and then ſhall Antichriſt the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of iniquyte come. Thys ſayeth Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome. Tertulian alſo,<note place="margin">Tertulli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> of the reſurreccion of the fleſhe: Who (ſayeth he) ſhall be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the waye? but the eſtate of Rome, whyche beynge cut awaye? and ſcattered into tenne kynges ſhall brynge in Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, &amp;c. For the departynge of kyngdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes from the Empyre of Rome, and the runnynge in of the rude Gotties, that is to ſaye of the Vandales &amp; Hunnies, dyd geue an occaſion vnto the Saracens, and vnto the Byſhoppes of Rome, for to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade and gette y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Empyre. For yf the one had not broken the ſtrength of the Empy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of Rome, the other had not raygned. But we haue expounded all theſe thynges more at large in the hyſtory here before.</p>
               <p>Nowe followeth the ruyne &amp; deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of Antichriſt.<note place="margin">Of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruccion of Antichriſt.</note> He ſhall not fall by and by after that he is ſtryken wyth a ſtroke or weapon, but by lytle and lytle, &amp; after
<pb facs="tcp:9420:46"/>
he hath bene made weake by many bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taylles he ſhall at the laſte peryſhe. But he ſhall not be caſte down w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mans hande, nother yet by the multytude of hooſtes, nor ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of ſouldyers, or gonne ſtrokes, but by the hande and power of God. For Chriſt ſhall fyrſte conſume hym wyth the ſprete of hys mouthe, and after that ſhall he put hym cleane out of the waye, wyth hys mooſt gloryous commynge into iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. The fyrſte of theſe two, dyd Paule take oute of the eleuenth chapter of Iſaie, whoſe wordes are theſe: With ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhall he iudge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, and wyth equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſhall he contende for the meke of the earthe, he ſhall ſtryke the worlde wyth the rodde of hys mouthe, and wyth the ſprete of hys lyppes ſhall he ſlaye the wycked. Nowe the ſprete of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouthe or of the lyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of God, is the true expoſycion of the worde of god. For the worde of God is the ſame ſwearde, wherewyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heade of thys proude Golyas ſhall be ſtryken of. For Antichriſt ſpeaketh on the ſyde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt hygheſt, and he ſayeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all that he doth, is deduced or taken out of the Decrees of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcrypture. For vnder the pretence of this, hath he hetherto raygned ſafely. But
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9420:46"/>
when that thoroughe the goodnes of God the lyght of the Goſpell, that is, Goddes worde begynneth to ſhyne, the clowdes of thys deceauer do ſtrayght waye vanyſhe awaye. For it is playne vnto all men, that thys fellowe in hys maners and lawes, is clene contrarye to Chriſte. Therefore it commeth to paſſe, that all godlye wytted men (the truthe once knowen) do abhorre and forſake hym. Therfore the ſwearde wherwyth this man is ſlayne is the word of God, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is he mooſt ſurely ſlayne, when that hys nature and dyſpoſycio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are manyfeſtly knowen by the doctryne of truthe. The knowlege of hym dothe kyll hym and caſt him downe, and the clokyng and ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of hym doth ſette hym vp. For they that knowe hym not, do beleue that he is an Apoſtolycall prophete, yee &amp; a god to, but they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knowe him trulye, are ſure that he is Antichriſte. The latter of theſe two dyd Paul take out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vii. chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of Daniell, where we reade: I loked tyll the ſeates were prepared, and the olde aged ſatte hym downe, and beholde, ther came in the cloudes of the ayre one lyke the ſonne of man, and he came vnto the olde aged, and the iudgemente was ſette
<pb facs="tcp:9420:47"/>
and the bokes opened. Then toke I hede therevnto becauſe of the voyce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proud wordes whyche that horne ſpake. And I behelde ſtyll, tyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the beaſte was ſlayne, and hys bodye deſtroyed and geuen ouer to be burnte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre. And therfore ſayeth Paule: Whom the LORDE ſhall deſtroy wyth the bryghtnes of hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his mooſt gloryous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng. For our LORDE ſayde in the Goſpell: Euen as the lyghtenynge commeth oute of the Eaſte, and appeareth vnto the Weſte, ſo ſhall the commynge of the ſonne of man be. For he ſhall come in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloudes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen wyth greate power and glory Math. xxiiii. And euen as darknes (as ſayeth S. Ierome) is dryuen away at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge of the Sonne,<note place="margin">The battail &amp; vanquyſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſte.</note> ſo ſhall the LORDE deſtroy and put hym awaye wyth the bryghtnes of hys commynge. Thys glorye and vyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye is reſerued vnto Chriſte onely. For they are deceaued whyche thynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, before the daye of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, ſhall by abolyſhed by the ſtrength of armes. But thys battayll betwene Chriſte &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tichriſte ſhall rather endure vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of the worlde. And he beynge bolde of the ſtrength of armes, ſhall breake a ſondre &amp;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:9420:47"/>
treade vnder hys fete the ſayntes of the mooſt hyeſt, but the membres of Chriſte ſhall wythſtonde hym, and ſhall ſette vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſwearde of the worde of God, ſhall bewraye hys deceate, ſhall accuſe his wyckednes, and ſo ſlaye hym. For by thys meanes ſhall he be put oute of mens har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and hys authoryte ſhall fall.<note place="margin">The vycto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in the truth of Goddes worde and conſtauncy.</note> And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeaſon, although he be ouercome, yet ſhall he take on, vntyll Chriſte the iudge ſhall putte hym quyte down. And therfore my brethren our vyctorye muſt ſtande al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>only in the truth of Gods worde, &amp; in the conſtanucy of our fayth. Therfore let vs betake our lyues vnto our faythfull crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, &amp; go forward in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> affyrmyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nical truth, &amp; glory of Chriſt ourredemer &amp; LORD, agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blaſphemies of this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure draggo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Chriſt wyll be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys, although he delyuer vs into hys handes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vvhoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge is by the vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of Satan, vvyth all povver and lyenge ſygnes and vvonders and in all deceueablnes of vnryghteouſnes amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that peryſh: becauſe they receaued not the loue of the truth, that they might haue bene ſaued. And therfore god ſhal ſende the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge deluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:9420:48"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:9420:48"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:9420:49"/>
beleue lyes: that all they myght be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, vvhych beleued not the truthe, but had pleaſure in vnryghtouſnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antichriſte raygneth by power and lyes.</note>Hetherto hath the Apoſtle entreated of the reuelacion of Antichriſt, of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yne and confuſion of hym: he hath ſpoken alſo of hys kyngedome and propertyes, &amp; nowe he turneth hym from that, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrybeth hys ſtrengthe and workes more at large. That deceauer ſhal come (ſayeth he) prepared wyth the ſprete and power of Satan, the whyche ſhall ſhewe forth them ſelfe in hym mooſt manyfeſtly. For thys maner of ſpeakynge <hi>Vvhoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge is by the vvorkynge of Satan,</hi> is ſo much to ſaye. Nowe the ſtrength and workynge of Satan ar chefely, murther, and lyes, as our ſaueoure ſayeth: He was a manſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from the begynnynge, and abode not in the truthe, becauſe the truthe is not in hym. Whan he ſpeaketh a lye, he ſpeaketh of hys owne, becauſe he is a lyer and the father of it. And Paule in this place ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge the workes of Satan by partes, doth teken vp power and ſygnes, that is lyenge wonders, and the deceaueableneſſe of vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryghteouſneſſe alſo. For Mahomet ſayeth that he is ſente of God in the ſtrength of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:9420:49"/>
armoure, &amp; for thys cauſe doth he deſtroye all thynges wyth fyre and ſwearde. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Byſhope of Rome hath abuſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armour of al kynges and prynces, perſecuteth and ſlayeth the ſayntes, ether callynge vpon the ſecular arme, or els by excercyſynge hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> owne ſtrength. The greate deſtrucci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mooſt ſtronge nacions nowe in our dayes do teſtifye what he maye do by ſtrength, and what murthurs, yee and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of kyngdomes, and robberyes, the deuell hath done in the world by hys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curemente. We maye thanke hys cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell and crafte, that here wythin thys .xxxvi. yeares, we haue ſene the ſtrengthe of mooſt ſtronge nacions, that is to ſaye of the Heluecians, Germanes, Frenchmen and Spanyardes, after they haue bene broken, to haue fallen now into the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Naples, nowe in the dukdome of Myllan, &amp; ſomtyme into other kyngedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, &amp; theyr kynges or prynces banyſhed or els ledde into captyuyte, mans lawes &amp; Goddes lawes plucte vp by the rootes, good ſtudye oppreſſed, mooſt noble cyties ſubuerted, and plentyfull contryes vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroyed: to be ſhorte, ther was none age ſpared. I do wyllynglye paſſe ouer
<pb facs="tcp:9420:50"/>
many thynges of the ſame ſorte, whyche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> membres of thys Byſhoppe, and the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall prelates wyth theyr compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, haue done in dyuers partyes of the world, and in many kyngdomes, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynces to the greate hurte of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune welthe and of all goodneſſe, and ſpecyally of the truthe. The prudente reader dothe well vnderſtonde by theſe thynges whych I haue noted, what he ſhulde do, beleue, or flye.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſygnes, and how his religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath ben greatly eſtabyſhed by them.</note>Nowe ther are two maner of ſygnes, true, and falſe. Thoſe are true, whyche are done in dede, and ſprynge oute of no phantaſye or imagynacion, but are wrought of God hym ſelfe by hys myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, for the ſtablyſhynge of the truthe. Suche are all the ſygnes of the prophetes and Apoſtles, of Moſes &amp; of Chriſte. And thoſe are falſe, whyche (by the ſufferaunce of God) are done by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynyſters or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of Satan, to the derogacion of the truthe or ſtablyſhyng of falſhed. And of theſe ther are diuerſe kindes. For ther are ſome whyche by a falſe appearau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue men. Ther are other whyche are done in very dede, as they ſeme to be, but for thys purpoſe, that they myghte leade
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:9420:50"/>
men away from the truthe vnto erroure. For the holy Apoſtle doth not call them onely lyenge ſygnes and wonders, whych haue a falſe ſymilitude or appearau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but thoſe alſo, whyche althoughe they be done in very dede, do yet brynge men vnto lyes, and deceaue the lokers on. S. Auguſtine hath diſputed more of ſygnes. <hi>In opere octoginta trium queſtionum. queſt. LXXIX.</hi> Our LORD Ieſus ſayeth in the xxiiii. chapter of Mathewe: Ther ſhall aryſe falſe Chriſtes and falſe prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and they ſhall do greate ſygnes and wonders, inſomuche that yf it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble, the very electe ſhulde be brought in to erroure. Beholde I haue ſhewed you before. Yf they ſaye vnto you, beholde he is in the wylderneſſe, go not out: beholde he is in ſecrete places, beleue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, &amp;c. Truely greate authoryte happened vnto Machometes relygion, throughe lyenge ſygnes and wonders. Nother yet hath the eſtymacion of the Byſhoppe of Romes relygio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, encreaſſed by ony thyng ſo much, as by the multytude of myracles. For by myracles hath he thruſt into the worlde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honourynge of ſayntes and worſhyppyng of ymages. For no man can well expreſſe
<pb facs="tcp:9420:51"/>
the wonderous craftes,<note place="margin">In this pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> author of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, called Henricus Bullinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus of Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gury had put in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers pylgre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mages of hys owne contrye. In the flede of whyche (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to vs) I haue ſet in theſe of oure olde acquayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute ony al alteracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the intent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he brought them in for.</note> wherwith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuel hath deceaued the whole worlde. They y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue at ony tyme vyſyted our Ladye at Wylſoon, Muſwell, Ypſwyche or Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyngame, the roode of comforte, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roode of reſt, the roode of grace in Kente, S. ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure at London, S. Thomas of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, or ſuche lyke Idolles: they haue ſene tables, oblacions and more teſtymonyes of myracles, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a great nauye of ſhyppes coulde carye awaye. For ſome one hathe crepte into the chappell of oure Lady, or ſome other ſaynte bothe croked &amp; lame, and there hath made hys petycion to an Image, and came home agayne in good healthe: and therefore in wytnes of thys thynge hath hanged vp hys ſtyltes before the Idolle. Another hath ſwymmed ſafe to lande fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſhyppewracke after he hath cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led vpon the helpe of ſome ſaynte, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hanged a table or a fygure of a ſhyppe before the Image. The thyrde eſcapynge of an hooſt of men of warre, made a vowe vnto the virgyn Marye, and dyd therfore dedicate hys harneſſe vnto her. Some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after they haue broken out of preſon, haue conſecrate vnto a ſayncte, ether a cheyne, or manacles or els a payre of fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9420:51"/>
Then came it to paſſe at length that not alonly thoſe temples, but all churches of Chriſten men were polluted wyth ſuch deluſions. Theſe falſe ſygnes occupyed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſte holy ſeates in Chriſtes churche, out of whyche the ſygnes and truthe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpell oughte to haue ben declared. For oute of ſuche places were theſe mooſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamefaſt lyes pronounced and ſhewed, wyth greate boldnes of the preachers, and wonderous reioycynge of the mooſt foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe people. What ſhall we ſay, that men haue ſayde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the very Images themſelues haue ether remoued out of theyr places, or els haue ben ſente of God hymſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or els where as they haue ben hyd in certayn places they haue come to lyght agayn. Some haue laught, and ſome haue wepte, other haue trembled &amp; geuen forth beames out of them, yee &amp; ſometyme they or theyr beardes haue wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully growe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in length or bygneſſe, ſomtyme they were gone clene awaye alone, and many tymes they haue ſpoken. And it was lawfull for no man to doubte, or els frelye, that is to ſaye truely to talke of, theſe thynges, yee a man had ſtonde in daunger of hys lyfe yf he had not worſhyppped and receaued theſe
<pb facs="tcp:9420:52"/>
wyckedneſſes as thynges that had come from God hym ſelfe, and ſet forthe to be worſhypped. Antichriſte that Byſhop of Rome not beynge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tente wyth theſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable thynges, and wyth the exteme ſuperſtycion and manyfeſte Idolatry of the people, dyd almoſte euery day con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate new Gods, that is (as they call it) canonyſed them, dyd ether inſtitute new pylgrimages, or els confirme ſuche as were inuented or receaued alreadye: he choſe oute relyques of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt ſtynkyng and wycked mens bones, and ſette them forthe to be worſhypped, yee &amp; promyſed pardon to the worſhyppers of them, and commaunded holydayes for thoſe fayned Goddes, &amp; lefte nothynge vndone which myghte encreace, noryſh, or ſet forth Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye: and dyd ſo corrupte the true rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that the very Gentyles were neuer muche more corrupte. Beſyde thys the prouable appearaunce and wounderous eſtymacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of falſe myracles dyd deceaue all the wyſeſt men in a maner.<note place="margin">How many good people haue ben de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaued lyke wyſe with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayned my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of Re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; Ipſwych.</note> It lacked but lytle, that we were not compelled to haue worſhypped in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſteade of true ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; myracles of God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſygnes &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, whyche certayne blacke frerers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:9420:52"/>
to the deuell had wyckedlye done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cytye of Berne in Nuchtlande, not wythoute the helpe of wytchcrafte you may be ſure. They wente already about the confyrmacion and approbacion of the Byſhoppe of Rome, and they had lyghtly obtayned it, but that the goodnes of God hauynge pytye on the ſympleneſſe of the people, dyd dyſcloſe thys myſterye of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyte to all the worlde before that it was fully fynyſhed and ended, to the deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion &amp; ſhame of oll other falſe myracles. I thynke that the buyldyng of theſe cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of beggynge Frerers, is one porcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chefe of theſe lyenge ſygnes. He ſhall not be beleued I know well amonge our poſteryte, that ſhulde tell them that beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in ſo ſhorte a ſpace, had buylded ſo large &amp; goodly houſes, of the whyche eche of them are ſufficiente for to receaue &amp; noryſhe kynges and prynces. But we ſe many thouſandes of theſe buylte vp on hyghe, and retched forth, bothe longe and large, and beſydes that to haue gotten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodlyeſt porcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of lande in all contryes and cyties. Yee and theſe deceauers the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, knowlegynge thys wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, do ſay: No prynce or kynge coulde perfourme in
<pb facs="tcp:9420:53"/>
certayne hundredes of yeares, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyche we beggers (not wythout myracle) haue fynyſhed in ſo lytle a ſpace. Yee and haue ſo fynyſhed them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> our buyldynges maye compare wyth the mooſt goodlyeſt olde places that are. God hath opened by this thynge (ſaye they) that the rules of oure orders do not ſo greatly dyſpleaſe hym: as thoughe Daniell had not ſayde longe ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me before, that thys ſhulde come to paſſe. For thus we reade of Antichriſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xi. chapter: Such as wyll ſerue hym, he ſhall geue greate worſhyppe and power, yee &amp; make them Lordes ouer manye, &amp; geue them the lande for naughte. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Paule addeth therevnto, in all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueableneſſe of vnryghteouſneſſe: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtonde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Antichriſte ſhall come after ſuche maner. That is to ſaye, when he commeth, he ſhall brynge wyth hym all kynde of iniquite, wherewyth he myghte brynge men away from the truthe, equy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, honeſtye &amp; ryghteouſneſſe, &amp; wrappe men in ypocryſy and erroures. We know therfore that by the meanes of antichriſt the commune iuſtice, all honeſtye, &amp; holy truthe ſhalbe moued oute of theyr place, &amp; vnryghteouſneſſe, ypocryſye, vnſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:9420:53"/>
voluptuoſneſſe, &amp; mooſt vayne perſuaſions to be ſet vp in theyr ſteade. Whyche thynges he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeyth not to haue all ages and degrees in poſſeſſion nowe at thys tyme, lacketh both hys eyes &amp; hys wytte. But all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall not be deceaued, but the reprobate: that is to ſaye, they, of whom the truthe was refuſed, and lyes receaued, that is to ſaye, ſuch as do wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully peryſhe. And becauſe that a ſecrete queſtyon myghte be moued:<note place="margin">Why y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt hath ſo greate power and proſperethe ſo greatlye.</note> Why hathe God ſuffered Satan, and Antichriſt hys captyue to haue ſo great power? By a ſolucion he preuenteth the queſtion and ſayeth: becauſe they receaued not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of the truthe, that they myghte haue ben ſaued. That is to ſaye: the iuſtice &amp; ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce of God, requyreth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thyng to be done. For theyr obſtynate rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſte Chriſte, deſerueth that all they whyche receaued not Chriſt, that of hys charyte was wyllynge to ſaue all men, &amp; for hys truthe ſake dyd ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe thynges whyche belonged to ſaluacion that they myght haue ben ſaued, ſhulde nowe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſufferaunce of God for the truthe haue falſhed, in the ſteade of charyte tyranny, and for a ſaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure haue a deſtroyer, and
<pb facs="tcp:9420:54"/>
that they ſhulde nowe beleue the lyes of a wycked man, whyche wolde not beleue Chriſte, that tolde them the truthe. For our LORDE hymſelfe ſayeth, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Ihon: Ye wyll not come vnto me, that ye myght haue lyfe. I receaue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorye of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but I knowe that you haue not the loue of God in you. I came in the name of my father, &amp; ye receaue me not, yf an other ſhall come in his own name, hym wyll ye receaue, Ioh v. And oute of thys truly it ſemeth, that that noble ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the commune people was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: They y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleued not Chriſte, ſhall beleue Antichriſte. And herevnto belonge alſo the wordes of Paule that followe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth he maketh that whyche goeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more clearer, ſayeng: <hi>And therfore,</hi> that is to ſaye, becauſe they receaued not the loue of the truthe, and were not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and followers of true relygio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>God ſhall ſende them ſtronge deluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> that is to ſaye, mooſt euydente ſeduccion and deceate, that euen lyke madde perſones, and men rauyſhed of theyr wyttes, they can not choſe but beleue lyes. And for thys cauſe <hi>that all they myghte be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,</hi> that is to ſaye torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; punyſhed,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:9420:54"/>
                  <hi>vvhyche beleued not the pure and ſymple truthe: but rather approued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryghteouſneſſe, ypocryſy, ſuperſtycion and erroure.</hi> Ye haue now a reaſon how it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe, that the worlde nowe a dayes is ſo readye to beleue the myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, doctrynes, and rytes of Antichriſte. It is the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of God, whyche hath ſhewed myracles ynoughe by hys ſonne, by hys prophetes and Apoſtles, and hath alſo preſcrybed vs doctrynes, and rytes clearlye and ſufficiente ynough. But all theſe thynges ſet aſyde, we had rather be deceaued. Therefore theſe preſtes and monkes Antichriſtes knyghtes, deceaued vs by gettynge awaye our moneye, and neuer ceaſſed to thruſte in theyr lyes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, vntyl y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had emptyed all mens cofers. Suche thynges as myghte be brought out of the Byble ſemed olde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worne thynges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all men daylye deſyred to heare new matters, and therfore was it fre for euery man that wold, for to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uente euery thynge that he lyfte. He was beſt alowed that had brought in ony new thynge into the churche: and ſo throughe theyr vnſhamefaſtneſſe, and our curyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyte and foolyſhneſſe, it came to paſſe, by
<pb facs="tcp:9420:55"/>
the ryghteous iudgemente of God, that all truthe was banyſhed many yeares ſence, and errour hath raygned myghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye thorow oute the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacions. Nowe though it be thus, and that experience it ſelfe do proue theſe thynges to be ouer true, yet are ther certayne euell occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyed perſones, whyche go about to boul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vp the corrupte captayns of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt corrupte relygion, whyche are bente to doſtroye the ſprete of the mouth of God. But the truthe which is inuyncible, ſhall ouercome bothe thoſe vayne prelates of the churche, and alſo theyr foolyſhe defen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders and ſhall alſo ouerthrowe them and bruſe them all to peces, excepte they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerte vnto the LORDE. Hetherto haue we diſputed more at large, then we thought to haue done at the begynnyng, of the commynge of Antichriſte, of hys kyngdome and confuſion, for the readers pleaſure, and for the erudycion and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the ſymple people. Nowe wyll we returne vnto Paule and the Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonyans. For Paule hymſelfe after he hath fynyſhed hys dyſputacion of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, turneth hym vnto the Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyans.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:9420:55"/>
                  <hi>But vve are bounde to geue than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes alvvayes to God for you brethren beloued of the</hi> LORDE, <hi>becauſe that God hath from the begynnynge cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen you to ſaluacion thorovve ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyenge of the ſprete, and thorovv be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuynge the truthe: vvhereunto he called you by oure Goſpell, to optayne the glorye of our</hi> LORDE <hi>Ieſu Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A notable place of the election.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Theophylactus knyttynge theſe thynges verye goodly with thoſe that are gone before, ſayeth thus: When he had ſhewed them certayne horryble thynges, and ſuche as myght amaſe the mynde of the hearers, he doth afterward eaſe theyr hartes, monyſhynge them after thys ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: Let other men be afearde of theſe thynges, they (I ſaye) whych peryſhe, and ouer whome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuell hath great power, but we are bounde to geue thankes for you vnto God, becauſe that he hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen you, and embraced you with his loue. And thys is a notable place of the elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of God. For God hath choſen vs vnto ſaluacion, and not that we ſhulde ſaye: yf God haue choſen me, I nede not feare dampnacion, and thoughe I ſynne neuer ſo muche. But God hath choſen vs
<pb facs="tcp:9420:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
vnto ſaluacion ſayeth Paule, whych ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion is fynyſhed in vs through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyenge of the ſprete and beleuynge the truthe: that is to ſaye, by the ſprete hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, whyche purifyeth our hartes, &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs true faythe. For fayth whyche is the gyfte of God, is myghtye in opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. Paule therfore doth ſet true fayth agaynſt the falſe perſuaſion, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyche Iames ſpeaketh, ſayenge: fayth wythout workes is deade. To thys matter of eleccion, belongeth the preachyng of the Goſpell alſo. For thorowe the preachyng of the Goſpell, he calleth vs to the true fayth, and to the optaynynge or poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the glorye of our LORDE Ieſu Chriſt: that is to ſaye, that we myghte be made the gloryous and bewtyfull poſſeſſion of our LORDE Ieſu Chriſt, an holy, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente and immaculate people, whyche myght honoure and worſhyppe God, and that God hymſelfe myght dwell in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of them that ſerue hym. For God hath not called vs vnto luſtes and vnclennes, i. Theſſa. iiii. but vnto holynes, &amp; pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and that we myght become hys holy te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. Theſe thynges ought to be taught vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregacions. After thys maner
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:9420:56"/>
ſuche as are captyue ſhulde be plucked out of the bondage of Antichriſt: and yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ony haue not fallen into hys captyuyte, let them here learne to geue God conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall thankes, and alſo to praye him that he leade them not into temptacion, but delyuer them from that euell, ſanctifye them thorow the ſprete, and by true fayth to kepe them in the eleccion of ſaluacion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therfore brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtande faſte, and kepe the ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces vvhych ye haue learned: vvhether it vvere by oure preachynge or by oure Epiſtle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nowe bryngeth he in that whyche he mente in the begynnynge of thys chapter where he ſayde: I beſeche you by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge of our LORDE Ieſu Chriſte, that ye be not ſodenlye moued from youre mynde, &amp;c. And in the meanſeaſon he dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth many thynges to thys effecte; and nowe at the laſte he bryngeth in &amp; ſayeth: In as muche as it is thus, abyde you in our ordynaunces whych we taught you, whether it were by mouth when we were yet amonge you, or els by myne epiſtles,<note place="margin">The Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles taught all theyr or dinaunces, ether by mouthe or els by epiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> whyche I ſente when I was abſent from you. For I taughte you the true Goſpell: ye nede not to ſeke ony other. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes
<pb facs="tcp:9420:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
do abuſe thys place, for the defence of mans tradycions. And we do graunte, that the tradycions of the Apoſtles, ought as well to be receaued as theyr epiſtles wrytten: but we do not graunte that all thoſe are the tradycions of the Apoſtles, whyche they do thruſte vnto vs vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the Apoſtles. The tradycions of the Apoſtles, are not contrarye to theyr epiſtles wrytten: but theſe mens trady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions are playne contrarye to the wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our</hi> LORDE <hi>Ieſu Chriſte himſelfe, and God our father vvhyche hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs, and hath geuen vs euerlaſtyng conſolacion and good hope thorovve grace, comforte your hartes, and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſhe you in all good ſaynge and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He dothe here after hys maner, vnto hys admonycion ioyne an happye and luckye wyſhe. And he doth here very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynglye brynge in together the whole ſumme of the Goſpel, that is to ſaye, that God hath loued mankynde, &amp; geuen him euerlaſtynge conſolacion, that is Ieſu Chriſte, whyche is oure hope, and hathe geuen it vs throughe hys grace, and not
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:9420:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for our merytes: that is to ſaye, that we myght lyue euermore. He wyſheth vnto them (I ſaye) that the ſame meke and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge God, wold comforte theyr hartes and ſtablyſhe them in all good ſayenge &amp; doynge: that is to ſaye, in all ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. For in theſe two thynges he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth all the offices or dutyes of a Chriſten man. And we Englyſhe men vſynge the ſame partycion do diuyde all ryghteouſnes into good ſayenge and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge, or into good wordes and workes. For theſe are thoſe good frutes, whyche ſprynge forthe of an harte that is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed thorowe the holy gooſt &amp; true fayth. Saynte Ambroſe marked the ordre of S. Paules wordes,<note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> and becauſe (ſayeth he) that the father, and the ſonne are one power and one diuinite and ſubſtaunce, therefore he doubted not to name oure LORDE Ieſu Chriſte fyrſte,<note place="margin">Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lactus.</note> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde God our father. And Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lactus noted that Paule dyd ſo ordre this prayer, that he dyd alſo preſcrybe them therwyth, what it became them to do: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, to geue themſelues, to ſaye well and do well, and to perſeuer in goodnes, and ſpecyallye to knowlege Chriſte to be the
<pb facs="tcp:9420:58"/>
onely hope, and euerlaſtynge conſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the faythfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Caput. iii.</note>
                  <hi>Farthermore brethren praye for vs, that the vvorde of God may runne abrode, and be glorifyed as it is vvyth you, and that vve maye be delyuered, from vnreaſonable and euell men. For all men haue not fayth, but the</hi> LORD <hi>is faythfull, vvhyche ſhall ſtablyſhe you, and kepe you from euell. And vve haue good hope of you thorovve the</hi> LORDE, <hi>that ye both do and vvyll do that vvhyche vve co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde you. And the</hi> LORDE <hi>guyde youre hartes into the loue of God, and lokynge after Chriſte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of prayer.</note>Ther is nothynge ſtronger in the ſyghte of God then a faythfull prayer, &amp; therfore doth he by all meanes moue the godlye vnto that mooſt dylygentlye. And here he ſendethe men vnto prayer alſo, in that mooſte troubleſome and wycked worlde, and in the great daunger of godly men. The truthe was preached in dede, but in the mean ſeaſon ther ſprange vp dyuerſe ſchiſmaes amonge them alſo, whyche wolde ſeme to be the followers of true relygion. And the open enemyes
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:9420:58"/>
of the catholyke relygio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd both ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyſhe the truthe, and alſo perſecuted the chefe ſetters forthe thereof mooſte cruelly: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lacked ther certayne hypocrytes &amp; falſe brethren, whyche were worſe then they, &amp; dyd muche more hurte vnto true godlyneſſe. For it is a true ſayenge, that an hypocrytycall frende doth more hurte then an open enemye. For of the one we take hede, and from the other we hyde no thynge. Therfore the greate dyſhoneſte, wyckednes, &amp; vnfaythfulneſſe that was vſed in thoſe dayes, dyd make the lyfe of Chriſten men, (whyche otherwyſe was ſharpe ynoughe) much more bytter. But Paule moueth men vnto prayer, &amp; ſayth: Conſyderynge the greate daungers that the worlde is nowe in, ther is none other helpe but turne vnto prayer. And he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrybeth the pryncypall thynges, whyche they ſhuld aſke of God by theyr contynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prayer. Fyrſte that the worde of God myghte runne abrode, and be glorifyed amonge all other nacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, euen as it was dyuulgate amonge the Theſſalonians, and receaued of godlye me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth an holy reioycynge. And all the ſcrypture beareth wytneſſe, that thys was the perpetuall &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:9420:59"/>
mooſt feruenteſte wyſhe or deſyre of all ſaynctes. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth chapter of the Actes of the Apoſtles, the Apoſtolyke church dyd aſke thys one thynge of God, that he wolde geue the apoſtles grace &amp; ſtrengthe to ſpeake the worde of God wyth boldnes. We offende greatly nowe a dayes, that we do aſke theſe thynges ſo coldlye of God: yee and I wolde to God that we dyd not vtterlye forgette to aſke them at all. Nowe where as he ſayde to runne abrode, he ſpake it after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune ſpeche, and he mente, that it might encreaſſe and ſpreade abrode apace wyth oute ony lette. And the worde is glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, when it is receaued of men, and all the glorye geuen vnto God onely. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de thynge that he teacheth to be aſked wyth prayer is, that we maye be delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from vnreaſonable and euell men: that is from inordynate and frowarde men,<note place="margin">Who vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable &amp; eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll men.</note> whyche do nothynge in theyr tyme and place, but all thynges peruerſlye. And the Apoſtle mente the enemyes of Gods worde, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothynge can pleaſe, and yet in the meanſeaſon they can do nothynge well themſelues. They fynde fautes, and peruerte all thynges, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praue
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:9420:59"/>
thoſe thynges whych are well ſayd and done, and do lade them and defyle them wyth ſhamefull ſuſpycions. They are alſo called ſhrewde, malycious and peruerſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And Dauid in hys pſalmes, dothe deſyre very ofte to be delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. And our LORDE dyd adde vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of that holy prayer: Delyuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euell: not alonly from the deuell, but alſo from all hys armye and bodye, and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally from that ſpyrytuall wyckedneſſe &amp; thoſe crafty deceauers. For ther is more ieopardye in a falſe frende and one that diſſembleth all thynge, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in an ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye.<note place="margin">Al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue not faythe.</note> And herevnto belongeth that which followeth: <hi>For all men haue not fayth.</hi> For this meaneth Paul: All they are not faythfull and true whyche wolde ſeme to be faythfull. For faythe in thys place is vſurped in the ſame ſygnifycacion that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Poete taketh it, when he ſayeth: <hi>Nuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> tuta fides,</hi> a man woteth neare whome he maye truſte. Yf ye wyll not grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t this maner of ſpeakynge, then thys is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge: Touchynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I do requyre your prayers ſo greatlye that we myght be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered from vnreaſonable and froward men, it is becauſe I knowe that ther are
<pb facs="tcp:9420:60"/>
many falſe brethren amonge you. For all they whyche pretende fayth, and profeſſe it wyth theyr mouthe, haue not the true fayth in dede. For oure LORDE ſayeth in the Goſpell. Math. xx. Many are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but fewe are choſen. And althoughe theſe two ſences dyffer not muche, yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte lyketh me better. Nowe ther fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. <hi>But the</hi> LORDE <hi>is faythfull, vvhyche ſhall ſtablyſhe you and kepe you from euell</hi> For leſte he ſhulde dyſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte the myndes of the ſaynctes through the vnfaythfulnes of manye: althoughe (ſayeth he) that ther be many vnfaythfull amonge you, yet the LORDE is faythful and true, whyche wyll kepe hys promyſe wyth vs, and be wyth hys for euer. They do reſyſte the Goſpell, but they ſhall not ouercome it: they lette it that it can not go much abrode, but they ſhall not dryue it cleane backe. They do betraye the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers of the truthe, but yet they ſhall not vtterlye oppreſſe the truth. For Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt whyche is faythfull is euer at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de for to fyghte for hys. He ſhall ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then hys agaynſte the vnhappyneſſe of theſe men, and ſhall kepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from euell. For as much as he is true, he wyll luckly
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:9420:60"/>
perfourme thoſe thynges, whyche he hath begonne in vs. Theſe wordes that are ſo full of conſolacion, ſhulde be often layde forth to ſuch as are in perrell &amp; are great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye aferde alſo of vnreaſonable and euell men. Nowe to mytygate and as it were to correcce, that whyche he ſayde before, he ſayeth: <hi>But vve haue good hope of you throughe the</hi> LORD, &amp;c. As though he wolde ſaye: We ſaye not theſe thynges becauſe that we doute of your conſtaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, no we do rather hope of you by the helpe of the LORDE Ieſus that thoſe thynges whyche I commaunde you of prayer, of watchynge and ſtedfaſtneſſe, ye both do and hereafter wyll do. And it hath muche grace wyth it, yf that in oure admonycion, we do reioyce of the thynge whyche we deſyre to receaue &amp; optayne, as it were receaued &amp; optayned already. Agayne, leſte that ony man ſhulde at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trybute ouermuche vnto theyr owne ſtrengthe, but that rather we ſhulde all knowe, that euery gyfte is geuen vs of God from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the LORDE (ſayth he) <hi>guyde youre hartes, into the loue of God, and lokynge after Chriſte.</hi> To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyhche Eraſmus dothe adde: Charite
<pb facs="tcp:9420:61"/>
ſhall cauſe you for to ſtudye to do good vnto all men, euen as God is benefycyal towarde all men. The lokynge for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge of Chriſte, ſhall cauſe you to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer all afflyccions manfully. Therfore in all trubles and perylles, we haue theſe two ſtyltes for to beare vs vp: prayer &amp; ſtedfaſte fayth. Brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let vs remembre theſe thynges I praye you, &amp; in as muche as our tymes alſo are mooſte corrupte &amp; troubleſome, and that for thys cauſe it is not poſſible but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes ſhuld be vexed, let vs praye to God, and conſtauntly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that he wyl neuer fayle vs: although that in the meanſeaſon many vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and euell men, do ether perſecute or betraye the truthe. God is true &amp; fayth full, whyche can not denye hymſelfe, and the truthe ſhall remayn euermore inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyble: let vs cleue therfore vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe, and we ſhall haue the vyctory, althoughe that when we be ouerthrowen of the worlde, we ſeme to be ouercome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vve commaunde you brethren in the name of our</hi> LORDE <hi>Ieſus Chriſte, that ye vvythdravve your ſelues from euery brother that vvalketh inordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, and not after the inſtytucion
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:9420:61"/>
vvhyche he receaued of vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is manyfeſte in the fourth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the fyrſte Epyſtle,<note place="margin">He condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth deli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es exhort the men to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure.</note> what gaue hym an occcaſion of thys commaundemente: That is to ſaye, becauſe that immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye after the tyme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles, certayn curious men beganne to thruſte them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the church of God, and vnder the pretence of relygion or euell ſciences and ſlouthfull ydelnes, dyd gette them a ſwete lyuynge. And where as befor in his fyrſt epiſtle, he dyd but eaſlye as it were bycker or ſkyrmyſhe wyth them: he dothe nowe comme in open felde vpon them, ouerthrowe them, and put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to flyghte. Fyrſte of all he ſettethe forthe the matter generally and ſayeth: I wyll not that you haue ony conuerſacion wyth inordynate fellowes, and ſuche as ordre themſelues otherwyſe then we dyd ordeyne. And he ſpeaketh not thys thynge ſleghtlye, but wyth greate authoryte &amp; pythye wordes, ſayenge: <hi>Vve commaunde you brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> After y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, leſte ony man ſhulde contemne hym, whan he thus commaundeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: he addeth to: <hi>in the name of our</hi> LORD <hi>Ieſu Chriſte.</hi> As thoughe he ſhulde ſaye: thoſe thynges whych we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde you,
<pb facs="tcp:9420:62"/>
we commaunde you not ſo muche in our owne name, as at the commaundement and expreſſe byddynge of Ieſu Chriſte. And nowe he recytethe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of Chriſte: that ye wythdrawe your ſelues from euery brother whyche beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth hymſelfe inordynatelye, that is to ſaye, not after the inſtitucion whyche he receaued of vs. We wyll ſpeake of that inſtytucion a lytle hereafter. Eraſmus ſayeth, that thoſe are brought into an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre, whyche are bounde to the commune lawe, and dyffer in nothynge from other men. And that it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarye to thys, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ony man the publyke lawes neglecte, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth at hys owne pleaſure. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paule ſhulde meane thys, by walkynge inordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natlye, the lyfe of Monkes, whyche is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued of vs agaynſte the inſtytucion of the LORDE and of the Apoſtles agreeth wyth thys in all poyntes. But when he commaundeth, that we ſhulde wythdraw oure ſelues from them, he commaundeth vs not to do as the Anabaptyſtes do, whyche ſeparatynge themſelues from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of ſayntes, do ſet vp a priuate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacion: but that we ſhuld flye theyr company as muche as we can, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9420:62"/>
that they myght be aſhamed &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue themſelues to be condempned for theyr ſlouthfulneſſe, and ſo be conuerted vnto the LORDE.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For ye your ſelues knovve, hovve ye ought to follovve vs. For vve be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued not our ſelues inordynatlye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge you, nother toke vve breade of ony man for naught, but vvroughte vvyth laboure and ſvveat both nyght and daye, becauſe vve vvolde not be chargeable to ony of you. Not that vve myghte not ſo do: but for to make our ſelues an example vnto you, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovve vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſhewethe by hys example what inſtytucion he had geuen them.<note place="margin">Paule labo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys own ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des.</note> He dothe alſo perſuade men to laboure, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pneth ydelneſſe. His wordes are playn. Althoughe (ſayeth he) I myghte well lyue at your coſte and ſtypende (for by breade he doth vnderſtonde meate &amp; drynke: yee and all ſuche thynges as belonge vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuſtentacion and neceſſyte of thys lyfe) yet had I rather to laboure both nyght &amp; day, for to ſhewe our ſelues an enſample and fourme vnto all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they myght followe vs. And by thys we maye ſe what
<pb facs="tcp:9420:63"/>
it is to walke inordynatlye,<note place="margin">To lyue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordynatlye.</note> and to be in ordre. They lyue inordynatly, whych are ydle and take theyr breade for naughte, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is to ſaye,<note place="margin">To lyue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynatlye.</note> lyke drone bees do eate vp o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens laboures. They lyue in ordre whyche wyth laboure &amp; ſweate do worke nyght and daye, that is to ſaye, contynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allye, and be not chargeable to ony man. The inſtytucions and rules of all ordres or Monkes,<note place="margin">Monkes.</note> after that they be touched, as it were with theſe holy thonderboltes, do fall flatte down. That whyche the ſame Paule dyſputed at Myletus, wyth the brethren of Epheſus, Actu .xx. agreeth well wyth thys.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For vvhen vve vvere vvyth you, thys thynge vve commaunded you: that yf ther vvere ony that vvold not vvorke, the ſame ſhulde not eate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">He that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boreth not, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſhuld not eate.</note>He reherſeth the ſame inſtytucion of hys, whyche he ſayde to be conteyned in the expreſſe wordes of the LORDE. And thys is the lawe: That he whyche wolde not laboure, ſhulde not eate. For ſlouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people deſerue none almes nother. For I thynke it not vnlyke vnto this law of God, whyche the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyles were wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te to ſaye in lyke prouerbes: <hi>Qui fugit mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:9420:63"/>
fugit farinam:</hi> he that flyeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mylle flyeth the meele, that is to ſaye: he that refuſeth to laboure, ſhal haue none of the vantage. And agayne: <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mel, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> apes.</hi> No bees, no honye. For yf ony man wyll not ſuffre bees, becauſe they haue ſtynges, he is vnworthye to haue ony ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye. And Mimus ſayeth in theſe wordes: Beare that whyche is greueous &amp; payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that thou mayſte haue that whyche is pleaſaunte and profytable. Wherfore Valerius maximus .ii. boke .i. chap. ſayth that the Maſſilians do kepe theyr gates ſhutte agaynſte all ſuche whyche vnder ſome pretence of relygion do go aboute to mayntayne theyr ydelneſſe. Yf that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges and rulers of Englande had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thys inſtytucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thre hundreth yeares ſooner, they had had more ryches &amp; fewer Monkes. Plutarche ſheweth in hys no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table &amp; brefe ſentence of the Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, that amonge them, the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and Goddeſſes be paynted and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured echeone wyth a ſpeare in theyr hande: In ſo muche that Venus herſelfe was in complete harneſſe. Sygnifyenge by thys, that not ſo muche as the goddes were ydle amonge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He ſayeth farther
<pb facs="tcp:9420:64"/>
that they haue thys prouerbe amonge them: Putte to thy hande, and calle on fortune, for ſo we muſt truſte on goddes helpe, that not wythſtondynge earneſtly we put to our dylygence ſo muche as ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in vs. For God heareth not the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the ſlougyſhe fylbellyes. Agayne it is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune ſayenge: God wyll helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wyll laboure. Farther more, he that hath learnynge or an occupacion, maye go where he wyll. Alſo that knowlege &amp; connynge is a hauen to men from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of pouertye, that is to ſaye: a ſcience or an occupacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the only remedy or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge for pouerte.<note place="margin">Eraſmus in adag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is: Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem queuis alis terra.</note> Wherfore they that are wyſe (I vſe the wordes of Eraſmus) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue ſubſtaunce ynough, wyll yet cauſe theyr chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to learne ſome occupacion, wherwyth yf they fall into pouertye, or ſhuld chaunce to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed theyr contrye, they myght yet get theyr lyuynge. Dionyſius a tyraunte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the Syracuſans after he was put out of hys domynyon, ſette vp a ſcoole at Corynthum &amp; taught chyldren learnyge and Muſycke. But now a dayes ther are many, whyche hauyng nothynge of theyr owne, do ſpende theyr tyme in rych mens
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:9420:64"/>
houſes, from whence yf they ſhuld be dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen oute, they muſte ether begge or ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le. Alſo thys place of Paule doth conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne all ſturdy beggers. I nede not to ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ony thynge of Monkes and ſuche ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifyers, as are vnprofytable to the godly mynyſtracion of the churche, ſeynge ther can nothynge be fayned whyche dothe more condempne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then thys.<note place="margin">A neceſſary exhortacion to prynces and rulers.</note> Ye pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and rulers of cytyes take good hede, that thys lawe of God be put in vre and haue place amonge you, yf that you loue the healthe of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune welthe. I pray you ſuffre not the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of your peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to be caſte vnto theſe puttockes to be deuoured, lyke me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that were bewytched vnder the pretence of relygion: &amp; wynke not alwayes at theſe craftye bryhers. Defende your people for Gods ſake, and brynge the lawe of god agayne into your commune wealthes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For vve haue herde ſaye, that ther are certayne amonge you, vvhyche vvalke inordynatly, and vvorke not at all, but lyue curiouſly. And them that are ſuche vve commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and exhorte by our</hi> LORDE <hi>Ieſus Chriſte, that they vvorke vvyth quyetneſſe, and eate
<pb facs="tcp:9420:65"/>
theyr ovvne breade.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Inordenate me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt be broughte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to an ordre.</note>He ſpeaketh nowe more playnly and ſhortlye that thynge, whyche he hath he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſet forth at large. The cauſe (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he) why I ſpeake of thys matter ſo muche, is, that I heare certayne men to be amonge you, whyche do walke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordynatlye: that is to ſaye, do no worke, but leade theyr lyfe curiouſly. Therfore we commaunde theſe men by our LOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DE Ieſus Chriſte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wyll get theyr lyuynge quyetlye, workynge wyth theyr owne handes. For thys thynge dyd the LORDE commaunde, Geneſ. iii. And condempned ydelneſſe for euer. We haue herde (ſayeth he) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther are certayne amonge you whyche do no worke at all, but geue theyr myndes to vnprofytable thynges.<note place="margin">Who do ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue curyouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye.</note> For to lyue curiouſlye, is to be buſy and laboure in vayne: as you wolde ſay, to be nother ydle, nor well occupyed: that this myght be the menynge: I heare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther be among you whyche worke not: for althoughe they laboure myghtelye &amp; ouermuche, yet theyr laboure is vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytable, and it were a greate deale better that they were ydle, then to be ſo euell occupyed. After thys maner we ſe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:9420:65"/>
Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes, Sacryfyers, and Nonnes to laboure a pace: for they ſynge &amp; mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vp prayers both daye and nyght, they watche &amp; leaue nothynge vndone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuche kynde of people ſhuld do: But in as much as Chriſt ſayeth, Math. xv. They wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe me in vayne, teachyng the doctry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes &amp; commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of men. Theyr laboure is vnprofytable, and to none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte. And ſo do the Anabaptyſtes crepe into all mens houſes, and reade &amp; preach both daye and nyght: but no man calleth them, nother do they ſtudye ſyncerytye &amp; and purenes, but do trouble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Vſerers alſo runne all aboute, and pull euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſleue and take greate payne: but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intente y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myght be ryche, &amp; lyue by the ſweate of other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For although that all theſe do laboure ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly, yet ther commeth no proſyte of theyr labour. For they do lytle good or none vnto theyr neyghboures. What ſayde I do no good? where as they not only do hurte, but are alſo the greateſt deſtruccion vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune welthe. Saynte Ambroſe deſcry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bynge a certayne kynde of curious men, of whyche ſorte we lacke none now a dayes, ſayeth: They whyche deſyre to be
<pb facs="tcp:9420:66"/>
ydle,<note place="margin">Of this ſort be theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers (as they ſeme) and they, whych fayn the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be banyſhed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe ſake.</note> go about to gette an occaſion, that they may make the ryche men fayne on them, &amp; to call them ofte vnto theyr hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and as they go vp and downe, they marke ſuttylly the doynges and opynio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of eche one, by thys meanes knowynge what they wold gladlye heare of euery man, that they may be fedde thankefullye and requyred alſo: whych kynde of doyng greatly abhorreth from the doctryne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> LORDE. For the bellye is the God of thoſe whyche gette theyr lyuynge by ſuch fylthye and ſhameles prouiſion. Hetherto is S. Ambroſe ſayenge. How much more doth it dyffer from the doctryne of the LORDE, that Monkes and ſacryfyers haue robbed the people, vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pretence of the name &amp; ſeruyce of God, and haue ſtuffed theyr bellyes wyth mooſt ſwete delycates &amp; deyntye dyſhes? Howe muche is it contrarye vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctryne of Chriſt alſo, that ſturdye beggers &amp; hypocrytes vnder the pretence of Chriſtes name do mayntayne theyr ydelnes, at the coſte &amp; charge of Chriſten men? We co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde and requyre ſuche (ſayeth the Apoſtle) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they worke wyth quyetnes, &amp; rate theyr owne breade: theyr owne breade (I ſaye)
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:9420:66"/>
as though he wolde ſaye, not other mens breade, but theyr own. For they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lyue cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riouſly do not eate theyr own breade but other mens. Farther more they laboure not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> quyetnes: for theyr laboure cauſeth trouble, in as much as it is vnprofytable &amp; chargeable to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myſerabe people. On y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſyde, neceſſary laboure brynge the wyth it muche quyetneſſe &amp; vtylyte: for he that goeth aboute hys owne buſyneſſe and worketh wyth hys own handes hath nede of nothynge .i. Theſſalo. iiii. And therfore is chargeable to no man, but doth geue to them that haue nede. Ephe. iiii. As many of you as are chargeable vnto the people, as many of you as do no worke at all, but go aboute thynges that be to no purpoſe, thynke ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thys is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto you alſo. Chriſte ſhall punyſhe you, excepte ye leaue your dyſhoneſt and mooſt vncomlye ydelneſſe, and gette you to laboure. And here is a goodly place, to ſpeake of the kyndes of laboures and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyneſſe, and of the helpynge and duetyes to the poore alſo. For all thynges are out of ordre amonge vs, but I had rather to ſubſcrybe vnto other better learned, then to ſhewe forth myne ignoraunce. Lewes
<pb facs="tcp:9420:67"/>
Viues hath wrytten two bokes of thys matter, in the whyche yf the rulers wold exercyſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynually, peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune welth ſhuld be in better caſe then it is, &amp; ther ſhuldbe leſſe ſlouth &amp; ydelneſſe, &amp; more laboure &amp; quyetneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ye brethren be not vverye in vvell doynge.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">We oughte to do good vnto al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The mooſt parte of the ryche me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do vſe to vpbrayde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore theyr ſlouggyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ydelneſſe, they other whyles not ſo euell or myſcheuous, as wretched and myſerable. And by thys prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they kepe theyr charite from them that haue nede of it. And therfore S. Paule ſayeth: I wyll not by thys meanes wythdrawe ony man from well doynge, or geue ony man an occaſion for to ordre myſerable people the more cruelly or vnge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlye. For me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought alwaye to do good. They ſhlud do well to euery man, but ſpeciallye vnto godly men, we wold not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God ſhulde be werye of our neceſſityes. We wolde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhuld receaue our ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requeſtes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Therfore we ſhuld not be weerye alſo, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hys me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres do call vpon vs for our helpe. And it is a pyteous thynge: yee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a very ydle perſon ſhuld pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:9420:67"/>
for hunger. Agayne they offende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctryne of God, whych are ouer fauourable vnto ſturdye vagaboundes. But good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can determyne this ſtryfe, equyte beynge theyr guyde:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yf ony man obeye not oure ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enges, ſende vs vvorde of hym by a letter: and haue no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany vvyth hym, that he maye be aſhamed. And counte him not as an enemye, but vvarne him as a brother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ordeneth a punyſhemente for the dyſobediente.<note place="margin">A payne is ordeyned for the dyſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diente.</note> Yf that ony man (ſayeth he) deſpyſeth to obey our inſtytucions, ſende vs worde of hym by Epiſtle, and in the meanſeaſon let hym be put oute of youre familiaryte: &amp; that for thys purpoſe, that after he is ouercome with ſhame, he may ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. For thys dyſciplyne is not ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſtruccion of ony man, but for his health. Therfore ye ſhall not vtterly putte from you a ſynner, but loue hym alwayes as a brother: but yet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſon ye ſhall monyſhe hym of hys faute and correcte hym. And oute of thys place we maye learne what the diſciplyne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche is, and vnto what ende it oughte to be putte in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e, &amp; alſo why the Apoſtle
<pb facs="tcp:9420:68"/>
doth commaunde vs to flye the company of the dyſobediente: not that we ſhuld ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre them as enemyes and wycked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not that we ſhulde preferre our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue other in holyneſſe, or els ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de well in our owne conceates, or exercyſe ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannye toward the myſerable people: but that he whyche is gyltye, beynge taughte through our wythdrawynge from hym, &amp; as it were warned of hymſelfe, ſhuld re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre hym ſelfe, and eſteme hys fylthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as it is in dede, and ſo beynge aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to amende. And yf that by the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the euell that raygned in hym he wyll not amende, &amp; by thys meanes come to hym ſelfe &amp; repente: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes take delyberacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amonge them, by what meanes thys madde man may be holpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leſte that ether he himſelfe do vtterly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe, or els infecte other wyth the ſame dyſeaſe. For they are deceaued whyche whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyſe that the auoydynge from hys company auayleth not, do ſet aſyde all farther remedyes, thynkynge that after thys, the churche maye vſe none other meanes to brynge them into the waye. But Paule ſayeth, ſende vs word of him by a letter. To what purpoſe I pray you?
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:9420:68"/>
That he myghte haue the name of hym that dyſobeyeth? But what profyte ſhuld come of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>? He wolde therfore haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of ſuche by an epiſtle, that he myght take wyth godly men ſuche counſell for thoſe vnruelye people, as they ſhulde thynke mete. For we ought all of vs to do our diligence that we deſtroye not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for whome Chriſte dyed, nother by our importunytie or cruelneſſe, nother yet by our ignoraunce &amp; neglygence. But theſe wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle ſeme vnto ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be vnderſtonde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> priuate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men: that is to ſaye, that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhulde abſtayne ſo muche as he coulde from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panye &amp; familiaritie, of ſuche as are dyſobedyente: And many haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded it of the open exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munycacion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The very</hi> LORDE <hi>of peace, geue you peace alvvayes by all meanes. The</hi> LORDE <hi>be vvyth you all. The ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lutacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of me Paule, vvyth myne ovvn hande. Thys is my token in all epiſtles. So I vvryte. The grace of our</hi> LORDE <hi>Ieſus Chriſte be vvyth you all. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He concludeth hys epyſtle, &amp; wyſheth them the bonde of al ryghteouſneſſe, holy peace, that they myghte kepe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alwayes
<pb facs="tcp:9420:69"/>
and in all theyr buſyneſſe For Satan is the author of diſcorde, chydynge, ſtryfe, enuye, and priuy hatred: and God is the author of concorde, mekneſſe, and chary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. He dwelleth wyth all ſayntes, ſo longe as they lyue in thys world in truthe and ryghteouſneſſe. Hys preſence is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of all goodnes, and hys abſence is the cauſe of all darkeneſſe, erroure, and eternall horror. Saynte Ambroſe ſayethe that for feare of choppers and chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers and corrupters of ſcryptures Paule doth teſtifye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he dyd alwayes ſubſcrybe hys ſalutacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in euery one of hys epiſtles w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his own hande: to the intente y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ony epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle receaued in his name, myghte not be ſuffered yf it were not ſubſcrybed wyth hys owne hande. The Apoſtles toke ſuch care, leſte that the congregacions ſhulde be deceaued by ony crafte or deceate. Theſe thynges do ſhewe of what cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayntie &amp; verite the Apoſtles wrytynges be. And becauſe that Paule dyd teache conſtantlye amonge all nacions y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde was ſaued by the grace of God, therfore he repetynge his wounte ſignet or ſubſcripcion dyd ſette to at the ende of all his epiſtles, this marke and ſeale of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:9420:69"/>
our faythe: The grace of oure LORDE Ieſus Chriſte be with you all. It appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: therfore by thys, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle vſed the helpe of a notarye or ſcryuener for to wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te hys epiſtles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſente.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Fautes eſcaped in prentynge.</head>
            <p>Werof the fyrſte nombre is the leafe, and A the fyrſte ſyde, B the ſeconde, the other nombre is the lyne.</p>
            <list>
               <item>iii. b lyne xxiiii. ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>- reade ſeruauntes</item>
               <item>iii. b lyne .xxvi. and to vſurpe. reade do vſurpe</item>
               <item>iiii. b lyne .xxii. accordyns, reade accordynge</item>
               <item>vii. a lyne .xxvii. ſay- he. reade ſayeth he</item>
               <item>vii b lyne .xviii myghtye engendre. reade myght</item>
               <item>xi. a lyne .xix. (as S. Ambroſe reade For (as S Am.</item>
               <item>xiii. a lyne .x departynge of fayth. reade from fayth</item>
               <item>xiii. b lyne .xxliii. ten kyngdomes. reade kynges</item>
               <item>xiiii b lyne .xxiii. he bowed read bouged</item>
               <item>xv. a lyne. xix. Lel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Sylla. reade Lucius Sylla</item>
               <item>xv. b lyne iiii. the halfe horne. reade lytle horne</item>
               <item>xvi. b lyne .iii Let vs therfore reade Let vs now ther.</item>
               <item>xviii. a lyne .xv. mad an ende. reade made an ende</item>
               <item>xviii. b lyne xiiii. Entichetis hereſy. reade Entichetis of</item>
               <item>xxxi. a lyne .xix. he had troden downe. reade hath trode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </item>
               <item>Item and hath publyſhed for had publyſhed</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:9420:70"/>
            <p>Here endeth the commentarye of Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Bullingerus of Tygurye vpon the ſeconde Epiſtle of ſaynte Paule to the Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyans, &amp; faythfully tranſlated into Englyſhe by R. H.</p>
            <q>Laus detur deo ſoli. Amen.</q>
            <p>Prynted in Southwarke in S Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas hoſpytall by Iames Nicol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Anno. 1538.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9420:70"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
